<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Angliae speculum morale The moral state of England, with the several aspects it beareth to virtue and vice : with The life of Theodatus, and three novels, viz. The land-mariners, Friendship sublimed, The friendly rivals.</title>
            <author>Preston, Richard Graham, Viscount, 1648-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 111 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55758</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3310</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5728</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11893576</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11893576</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50479</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55758)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50479)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 507:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Angliae speculum morale The moral state of England, with the several aspects it beareth to virtue and vice : with The life of Theodatus, and three novels, viz. The land-mariners, Friendship sublimed, The friendly rivals.</title>
                  <author>Preston, Richard Graham, Viscount, 1648-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 187, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Herringman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Emendanda on p. [188].</note>
                  <note>Imperfect copy: The Life of Theodatus, and three novels, viz. The land-mariners, Friendship sublimed, The friendly rivals lacking in filmed copy.</note>
                  <note>Page [188] is stained with some loss of text in filmed copy. Pages 166-end photographed from Huntington Library copy and inserted at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50479:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50479:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Angliae Speculum Morale;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Moral State OF ENGLAND, WITH The ſeveral Aſpects it beareth TO VIRTUE and VICE. With the LIFE of <hi>THEODAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> And Three Novels, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>The LAND-MARINERS,</item>
                  <item>FRIENDSHIP SUBLIMED,</item>
                  <item>The FRIENDLY RIVALS.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>!</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh veré Phrygiae, neque enim Phryges!</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Herringman,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Blew Anchor in the lower Walk of the <hi>New Exchange,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:50479:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50479:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be thought that theſe enſueing Characters are meant for reflexions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on particular perſons: but I here aſſure the World that I onely ſtrike at general practices. I do no more then what my ſelf would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receive from any hand; and I ſhall always write his name with the first, in the Roll of my friends, who telleth me wherein I have tranſgreſs'd: for they are moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py who are most innocent; now
<pb facs="tcp:50479:3"/>ſince humanity is naturally prone to ill, it ought to be our care to avoid and hate it, and the way to do ſo, is first to know it. I think he who ſtriveth to wound his Brother's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimation, at the ſame time stab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth his own; for thus he brandeth himſelf with the infamous name of a malicious perſon, and is avoided by all as noxious to civil Converſe. Most ages have brought forth thoſe publick ſpirits, thoſe friends to their Country, who have diſſected Vice, and ſhew'd it in it's ugliest colours: of most note amongst the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents were <hi>Juvenal, Perſius, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race;</hi> and almoſt every Age and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Nation ſince have been hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in ſuch, and doubtleſs they wrought a greater Reformation with them down right blows then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pyth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ras, <hi>Socrates, Plato,
<pb facs="tcp:50479:3"/>Ariſtotle, Theophraſtus;</hi> nay, then that profeſs'd Maſter of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thicks <hi>Zeno,</hi> or any of the nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Schools of Moralists have, with their moſt perſwaſive reaſons. Vice from the least of familiarity ſlipp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into an habit, and in the end infatuateth; and how it hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated it ſelf into the affections of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> nay, how it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate with their Natures, their daily actions ſhew. The Nations obstinacy I fear is a ſad preſage of it's fate: for it turneth not from its wonted courſes, though the will of Heaven hath been ſpoken in Plague, and War; nay, though't hath giv'n its commandment (like the Levitical Law) in a dreadful Fire. And we know that God hardened <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s heart before he drowned him, and his hoſt in the red ſea. In
<pb facs="tcp:50479:4"/>this juncture of time it reſembleth <hi>Criſpinus</hi> in the account which <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venal</hi> gives of him in theſe words;
<q>
                  <l>Ecce iterum <hi>Criſpinus,</hi> &amp; eſt mihi ſaepe vocandus</l>
                  <l>Ad partes, monſtrum nulla virtute redemptum</l>
                  <l>A vitijs, Aeger, ſolaque libidine fortis.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If I can by theſe Lines oblige my Country-men to better courſes, I ſhall attain my end; if I cannot, I have done my duty as a free-born Subject, who ought to be ſollicitous for his Countrys good. The expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced may ſee farther then the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Rays of my young Eyes will reach; for I pretend to ſet down no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing here but what is obvious to the weakeſt ſight.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="gender">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50479:4"/>
            <head>MAN.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He tranſactions of this World are the moſt unpleaſant ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that ever enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd my mind. All affairs do reſemble the great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chines of Heaven and Earth, in their motion and volubility, but not in their regularity; for the Sun riſeth from the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> at noon viſiteth the <hi>South,</hi> and maketh the <hi>Weſt</hi> his Bed; the Moon ſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not from her appointed li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, obſerveth her times of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50479:5"/>Change, and influenceth the Sea; that alſo keepeth its hours of flux and reflux; and generally the whole off-ſpring of Nature mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth as at firſt, but only Man, who was deſign'd Maſter of the whole, though he partaketh of the Heavenly ſoul, liveth in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non to all Laws and Sanctions of God, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, runneth a courſe contrary to all Order; and in his Actions, if not in his Heart, ſaith, Tuſh, there is no all-ſeeing Providence, no God. Tis true, the whole progeny of <hi>Adam</hi> is obnox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious to his original guilt: but Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is the Lavre of Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; we have innate affections, and propenſities to do evil, ſince our Mothers converſ with the ſerpent; But Grace is in the World, which will reſine our natures. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50479:5"/>no evil is in us, but the cure is in our own power: no poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Herb (as Naturaliſts obſerve) ſprouteth out, but in the ſame field its Antidote is plac'd. 'Tis a prodigie that Men ſince they know they have a rational ſoul which is to meaſure out Eternity, and after, according to the habits and inclinations it ſerv'd moſt here, is to receive a Crown, or a Scorpion, ſhould follow the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of Sence, wholly depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Reaſon from her Empire o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the paſſions, and be as Kings, (though partaking of all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies of Humanity) for one hour, to be afterwards moſt miſerable for Myriads of Myri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ads of ages, which like a Circle will never have an end. Did not Heaven oftner ſtretch out a ſtaffe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50479:6"/>then a rod, apply <hi>Gileads</hi> Balme, then purſue revenge: the World had many Centuries of years ſince been paſt the frontiers where now it ſtands, and immerſed in the very centre of the Valley of Tears and Death.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Adam</hi> through the wide Organs of the depraved ſpecies, the ſad effects of his fate are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd to all; but yet theſe Miſeries by the mercy of Heaven being ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; every heady appetite which we careſs, and embrace, is the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent which betrayeth our ſouls anew into that infinity of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies which attendeth the eating of forbidden fruit. Theſe unhappy, and often repeated acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, have created parallel habits in us, which have changed the whole Maſs of our Nature, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50479:6"/>have ſet us in a diametrical op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to all that is called good: to prove this, if we examine the intrigues, and daily occurrences in the World, we ſhall find nothing, if apply'd to the Divine Rule, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable, nothing if laid in the ballance of the Sanctuary, of juſt weight; every rational Being, like the ambitious Angels, hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the intent of its creation; none but ſenſitive and vegetative Creatures purſue the primitive end of their inſtitutions.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>There is no Medium betwixt good and evil.</l>
               <l>They admit of no mixture, or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual commerce.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Whoever is not good, is its contrary; if a good Action be leaven'd with the leaſt Vice, it is overcome by its powers, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50479:7"/>degenerateth into bad: the leaſt Sin ſtamps Ignominy on the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Virtue; the Scripture ſays, He who breaketh but one Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, though he have invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olably obſerved all the reſt, is guilty of the breach of the whole Table.</p>
            <p>If thus then; alas, what ſhould we be if all our actions were put to the Teſt! how few do oblige without the hope of a threefold return? who loves without a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual, or avaritious end? who will ſerve their King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try without the hope of Reward from him, or applauſe from her? in fine, we undertake nothing but we conſider our ſelves firſt; and if we cannot work our own inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, we will let the other fall, though of the moſt publick na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50479:7"/>We obey no Parent but the Fleſh; we hugg no Brother but a ſon of <hi>Belial;</hi> we know no Friend but the unrighteous Mammon: but oh deceived Man! thy blind Parent will lead thee, as blind, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an ocean of Maladies, and Miſeries, thy Brother to a Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, or a Gibbet, and thy Friend wil hinder thee from ever behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Heavenly manſions. Oh! where muſt diſtreſſed Virtue plant her feet, if thus incroach'd upon? where muſt ſhe be found if her Antagoniſt thus in Triumph exalt her crowned head? ſure like <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> no where but above the Starrs. To conclude with the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollarie of the whole, every acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Man is impertinent; he draweth no Line to its true Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre; he levelleth all his deſigns at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50479:8"/>a falſe end, and wandreth in thoſe broad paths which conduct to the gates of Deſtruction.</p>
            <div type="profession">
               <head>The Noble-Man.</head>
               <p>HE who is advanc'd to Title and Fortune, and is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an head of the people, either by his own merits or the atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Anceſtors, ought to be exemplary in virtue. Being ſet by Heaven on ſuch a conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous place on purpoſe to guide the people into the paths of love, and obedience to their God, and King; and to ſhew them the ill effects of contrary performances: like Candles put at night in <hi>Pharos</hi> Towers, which at once give the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiners a view of their fruitful <hi>E. gypt,</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50479:8"/>and lead them off thoſe many and dangerous ſhelves of the <hi>Nile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No Nation ever boaſted a bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, a more gallant, a more virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Nobility then <hi>England;</hi> who have rais'd eternal Monuments in forreign parts to their Country and themſelves, witneſs their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures in the Holy wars, their conqueſt of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> their many attempts upon the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourous <hi>Scott,</hi> before the happy union of the Crowns; of late times in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> before we got footing there, on the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, our exploits in <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Portugal</hi> will ſpeak; at Sea in the Spaniſh invaſion; and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remarkable Encounters there and elſewhere. But yet, though they have gain'd Honour and a deathleſs Fame, why ſhould it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50479:9"/>to an Adulterate and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſticate poſterity? why ſhould they inherit their Glories who do not their Virtues? who can boaſt onely of the empty name of a deſcent from Noble and gallant Loins? 'tis not fit that Tiſſue and Arras which have adorn'd Palaces ſhould hang on the Clay-walls of a Cottage, becauſe the Duſt of the one would Eclipſe the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the other; no more is it ſo, that they who are fallen from the Glories of virtuous Fathers, ſhould bear thoſe Eſcutcheons which they tranſmitted to them fair and white, leaſt they cloud them with that black ignominy which reſults from vitious practices; Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as well as Friendſhip requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Virtue for a Baſis.</p>
               <p>I wiſh this diſcourſe could
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50479:9"/>not ſeem to appertain and be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the now <hi>Engliſh</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſs ſo much as it doth: (with the pardon of ſome few, to whoſe conduct and generous integrity, <hi>England</hi> muſt own much of her preſent happineſs, and owe much of her future.) but this being no private concern, but one of ſo publick a Nature, that every free-born Subject ſeemeth to have a ſhare in their carriage, they being the Pillars of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as they are Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of the King; I muſt take notice of it. Tis now by the great ones thought putid pedan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, to be skill'd in Arts or Arms; they leave the practice of thoſe to the plodding Students, of theſe, to the ſoldier who ſights for pay; ſo putting at once their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50479:10"/>Nations Glories, and its fortunes into unexperienced and mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hands. They in their lives imitate the ſoftneſs they tryed in their Cradles: they are pierc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Northern blaſt, blown down with the ſound of a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet; nor did ever any Action of theirs ſpeak them valiant, but the beating a Lacquey who dares not reſiſt, or the kicking a poor Tradeſman down the ſtairs whom they had undone before. Theſe ſure are virtues exceeding all thoſe for which ſtorie gives their Anceſtors a Fame. Religion is a thing they explode converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it merits not their thoughts, yet they build Groves to the Gods of this world in high places, and build Altars, and with a more then heatheniſh ſuperſtition pay
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50479:10"/>ſacrifice to the weakeſt of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Sure theſe are greater Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries then the ſon's of <hi>Nebat,</hi> though he made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin. Luxury hath obtain'd above all; they eat, drink, and play, but think not to morrow they muſt die. Thus their manners are not onely become effeminate, but their bodies and their ſtrengths are decayed. Their Fathers fed upon thoſe corroborating meats the Iſland did afford, (which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, if ever any was, is a moſt fortunate one) and they ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thizing with them, gave them the moſt natural force; but theſe not content with what in ſuch abundance it offered, have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered our Nation to be invaded with forreign ſoftneſſes, and to be cat up with <hi>what it ſelf was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50479:11"/>intended for food,</hi> for nothing, it is ſure, conſumeth our bodies more then theſe; and our Eſtates muſt ſuffer if we entertain a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce for what turns to no profit, but ends in a loathſome excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; then to conſummate this happineſs, a French Cook muſt prepare the viands; moſt of their other Menials being of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; (who are the moſt naſty naturally, and the moſt falſe of all the Europeans,) terming their own Countrey-men not agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or adroit enough; thus they ſuffer their poor Natives to ſtarve, whilſt they ſeed a people whom God hath placed in a Clime which giveth them even a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous maintenance: Fornication is no ſin with them, and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery is the leaſt; they not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50479:11"/>in every ſuch Act, that they invade their neighbours free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold: Theſe cuſtomes accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied them home who were ſent out ſo young that they could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marque nothing but the vices of a Countrey, and ſure it were a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration worthy of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to enact, that either (with the Lacedemonian State) they ſhould not travail at all, or not till they are come to ſome maturity. Is it not fine, that when the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion calleth for their heads or hands, they ſhould be employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the one, in beholding the the imaginary beauties of an eye, and the other, in the worſe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a mean, and loathſome, yet commanding Leachery; where will theſe follies end? doubtleſſe no where but in their ruines who
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50479:12"/>foment them; will it not by theſe practices come to paſs, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall be more deſpicable in the eyes and mouths of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple then the Nobility? thoſe who were their Countreys great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Glory, and delight, will in time become its greateſt ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and hate; there is no return to loſt Glories; the deſcent to Hell is eaſie, but the coming back impoſſible; the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Angels, (though they wrought their fates by Nobler means, by ambitioning higher honors) muſt now wear out eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in everlaſting Chains and Darkneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="profession">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:50479:12"/>
               <head>The Courtier.</head>
               <p>AS his Obligations are greater to his Prince; and his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages more immediate from him, ſo ought his affections to be more fixed to, and centred in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, and his ſervices to be of greater volume then thoſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; for though the Great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of Heven and Earth will be praiſed by us his mean ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects here, yet the Angels whom he honoureth with a nearer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, with more cloſe approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to his radiant Majeſty, give him more magnifying praiſes, more elevated Halleluiahs. He who truly intends to make a Court the Scene of his life, ought above all to practice ſincerity,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50479:13"/>and to value his faith; for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes of the people to their Sovereign of all kinds being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd through him as a conduct, it ſhould be his care that they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at the Royal Ear without addition or diminution; leſt he wrong them in their affairs, and ſo alienate their affections from him to whom they are due, and purchaſe to himſelfe in the end ſhame, if not death. He ought to appear in a garb not above his place, for ſo he may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure envy to himſelf, nor below the dignity of his Maſter, leſt he wrong him; He ought to uſe all means to advance him in the affections of the people, to indear his intereſt to them, to exerciſe an obliging mien to all; but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to forreigners under
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50479:13"/>what Character ſoever they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main here, to ſhew himſelf in all ſplendor due to the Office he hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, to them, that he may create a Reverence in them for the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it. He muſt be ſeen in the intrigues and intereſts of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marine ſtates, and know their benigne and malevolent Aſpects one to the other; to be ready upon all emergencies to meet the maladies of the body poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick by his Head or Arm; to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſe its fortune onely, and to do his devoir to it by freely ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing his life, and poſterity, and by returning without regret, his goods to that ſervice from whence he received them; imitating in that his Maſter who though he hath large incomes from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yet reſtoreth them by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50479:14"/>them upon all exigencies for their good, as the Sun draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth off exhalations and vapors from the Earth, but ſendeth them into her Lap again in gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and fruitful ſhowrs, which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt her nature, and make her bring forth in larger proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>But 'tis wonderful to ſee how farr men are from what they real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ought to be, his moral parts ſeem to be ſubject to the ſame vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitudes with the ſtate he fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; for now you ſhall behold him like the lazy <hi>Leviathan,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his ſport in the deepeſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſſes of pleaſure, preying upon thoſe ſmaller Fiſh whoſe ſtrength cannot reſiſt his power: he is drowſie and backwards to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of his Prince, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50479:14"/>vigilant for his own; he runneth in ways excentrique to all Vertue, and knoweth no Friend or Divinity but <hi>Venus, Bacchus,</hi> and his Mammon; his motion is perpetually in bowing and cringing, but he is as conſtant in directing his Eye to the pole of his intereſts, as the magnetick Needle is to the <hi>North;</hi> he is that true Chymiſt who extracts by the calcining fire of his feigned-ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent affections, gold out of the bleeding eſtates of unhappy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents, and of thoſe whom the Law adjudgeth to puniſhment, and ſometimes of innocent offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and pretended Criminals; But though theſe may be the principles of ſome, yet there are many whoſe integrity, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50479:15"/>fidelity to their Prince renders them worthy of thoſe advantages they enjoy: yet their carriage cannot excuſe others. There is an impertinent thing called a young Courtier, whom I ſhall draw as near the life as I can.</p>
               <p>His diſcourſe is that which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneth the ears of the Good, and the wiſe, and proveth trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome even to the moſt imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; his remarques are of the moſt inconſiderable encounters of the day, in which himſelf is always a principal Actor; either how many Women by his falſe vows he hath overcome; or where he hath made the greateſt debauches in <hi>Burgundy</hi> or <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigne,</hi> at <hi>Jero's, Shattelin's,</hi> or <hi>Lafroons;</hi> or if his happy inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50479:15"/>doth ſupply him with a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorted <hi>Rebus,</hi> or an ugly diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Anagram, an unnatural An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titheſis, a forced quibble, or an uncivil repartie that bites ones re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, (which all are the dry ſcabs of a corrupted wit,) he muſt be admir'd for being Maſter of a greater ingenuity than <hi>Ben John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> He is ſure to have three or four verſes of Love and Honour ready out of the lateſt Play, and the laſt new Song in his poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, which he hath coppied in falſe Engliſh. 'Tis fit his dreſs ſhould be gay, becauſe Embroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deries are for the Palaces of Kings; but it is not fit that many poor families, to ſupply his extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancies, ſhould want bread: 'tis miſerable to think that a thouſand curſes ſhould attend his ſteps and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50479:16"/>not one good wiſh ſhould be ſent up for him: but why ſhould pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be offered for him who never prays? who contemneth Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a vile thing? who never nameth God but in his Oaths or Burleſque.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="profession">
               <head>The Gentleman</head>
               <p>IN the frame of the State, is like the Tuſcan Pillar in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitecture, which though it be not ſo Polite as the other Orders, nor can boaſt a well proportion'd neatneſs, like the <hi>Ionick,</hi> nor an handſomely adorn'd head, like the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Column, yet it is in building the foundation of all
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50479:16"/>their Beauties; ſo though he be inferiour in Title, yet in Power and intereſt he is equal if not ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to the Nobleman; for in all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords we find the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to have been very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the Government, though the Lords make a Court of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature; it is his Duty to ſerve his Countrey by his Preſence there, to preſerve her Peace, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend her Priviledges and Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities; to be hoſpitable to his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digent neighbours, to receive the ſtranger and way-faring-man with Chearfulneſs and Civility: In fine, to open his Napkin to all, and not to employ it in wrapping up his Talent. But alas! is it not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, that Vanity like <hi>Romes</hi> Eagles at the Meridian of her power, ſhould carry Conqueſt on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50479:17"/>her Wings to all places where ſhe is pleas'd to flee? who of the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt? nay, what Diviner (if any ſuch there be) could have fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen, that vice ſhould have found out the once Sacred Groves, the quiet and innocent receſſes of a Countrey? the Gentleman now hath chang'd the Plow and Cart, which did feed his Grandſire, and a brave Train of ſtout attendants in his great Hall, whoſe Labour well deſerv'd their Hire, for a Gilded Coach, and a numerous Train of debauch'd and inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicant Lacqueys, and now by an unhappy Thrift hath converted his long Table well covered, and well filled, into a little round one, which holds one Diſh and three People, and hath turn'd his great Hall into a little Parlour:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50479:17"/>He once in a year arriveth at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> with his Lady, a rich or hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Daughter, or a Neice, with whom they fail not daily to viſit the Theatre, giving to her the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments of the Town, who ought rather to be ſeen in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of a Countrey life. If her fortune be great, 'tis unfortunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhip-wrack'd upon ſome Lord; who after the enjoyment of her revenue, loaths her perſon; He places his Son perhaps at the Inns of Court, who knoweth he is to heir an Eſtate, and thinketh it but waſhing the <hi>Ethiops,</hi> to injure his Brain with the ſturdy Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and knotty Maximes of the Law: he therefore girdeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for other accompliſhments, allotting the morning to dance or fence, at noon he dineth, in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50479:18"/>afternoon he ſees a Play, and to recreate his languiſhing ſpirits, he locketh up the day with fat va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porous Ale at <hi>Hercules</hi>'s Pillars and maketh there his <hi>non ultra</hi> till 12 a clock! After two year, when he returneth to his Father and ſhould give him the Harveſt of the ſeed, which in ſuch proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he hath ſown, he hath not Wit nor Law enough to keep his own Courts. The Gentleman commonly viſits the Town at the expence of the poor Labourer's ſweat, whom he hath now wrack'd to the utmoſt farthing; he liveth ſplendidly here for ſome moneths, he drinketh at all hours, he fitteth at the head of the Table, and for his honour disburſeth for the reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; if well heated, he may, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily, be invited to ſport with the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50479:18"/>frail Dye, and there he is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaluted with a high or low Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam; or ſome other convenient inſtrument of execution; if his Genius leadeth not that way, he goeth to viſit a Lady of Quality, an acquaintance of his Friends, who for that occaſion is well dreſs'd in her borrowed weeds, and hath Lodgings in ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh place, as the <hi>Piazza, South-hampton buildings,</hi> or <hi>Suffolk ſtreet;</hi> but is ſuch a Creature, as will be at the beck of any Coachman, rather than he fallow; if he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with her, he is either clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, or payeth for his familiarity, with Silver, Gold, Watch or Ring, whatever moveable he hath about him, and when he is laid to ſleep, his Landabrides and his dear friend divide the ſpoil: when
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50479:19"/>his whole Cargo is ſpent, then he either abſcondeth, or without rigging, or ballaſt, ſneaketh pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately in a Stage-coach to his houſe in the Countrey, (his own being ſeiſed) and by the next Term is preſented with an Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, from his Taylor, or Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord, and perhaps too from his Apothecary. Theſe ſurely are great miſtakes, and mighty im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies, and much diſſonant from the nature of that Province with which Heaven hath endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. To conclude, if the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans fortunes Sympathize ſo much with the Peaſants, that if the one faileth, the other falleth, much more muſt the States with his, who is her chief corner-ſtone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="profession">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:50479:19"/>
               <head>The Gallant or Hector</head>
               <p>IS he who maketh Vice his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; who recreates himſelf with dangerous follies; who feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon his greateſt enjoyments with Heaven's ſword of juſtice hanging over his head by a very ſlender hair of Mercy. It is his chief principle to eſpouſe none, long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then it indulgeth his unhappy deſignes. He apprehendeth Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be a thing dreſs'd up in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Rites and Ceremonies, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to terrify the ignorant vulgar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to obedience; grant there be a God, ſaith he; doth he require greater performances of us than our Nature will bear? doth he give us affections to indulge, and muſt not we gratifie them? in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50479:20"/>making the true uſe of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we adore the Creator; we praiſe the Cauſe by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Honour to the Effect; but he who thus argueth, conſidereth not that all theſe Bleſſings are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with a limitation, leſt we might be ſo wholly intent in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nature, that we might be forgetful of the Author of it; nor remembreth he that nothing is created perfect; that <hi>Adam</hi> was authoriz'd by his Maker to Treat his ſence with any Tree of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice, but one; he cometh to Town innocent enough, but by often converſing with Pitch, he at laſt retaineth it upon his Hands and Cloaths; he is, for the moſt part a younger Brother, who hath ſpent what his Father left him to ſubſiſt by; or a Reform'd ſoldier,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50479:20"/>who having liv'd in the War, muſt when that Harveſt is ended, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in the Autumne, if he uſe nor ſome pious fraud which will give him meat; in order to live, he procure an intereſt in the Groom-Porters, or an Ordinary, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth theſe the Scenes of his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture atchievements: it is then his care to have intelligence of young Gentlemen of fortunes, who ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at Town, that being known, he intrudeth into their company, and gaineth an intereſt, by obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them by looſing ſome ſmall ſumm at firſt, as Fiſhers bait the waters over night, with hopes of a large return for theſe charges in the morning; and thus taketh a ſeverer uſe then the <hi>Jews</hi> do of thoſe out of their own pale, if any of them do not play, (which is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50479:21"/>ſeldom ſeen;) he procureth him a Miſtreſs, who certainly clappeth him, then he ſhareth with the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon, who maketh his Cure more dilatory, and at the ſame time fluxes his body and his purſe. And now, upon the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of this good Office, his friend advances, (pretending his ſervant out of the way) to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a trifling ſumm of 20 or 30 Guineys, which if asked for by the Creditor after the forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of 6 or 7 moneths, he is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd <hi>D' Dam-me</hi> Sir, you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oblige your friend, and you injure mine and your own honour; but when at laſt he findeth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge groweth on him, he taketh a ſmall occaſion to quarrel with him, and ſo the League of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is broken; Foreſight and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50479:21"/>Conduct he throweth behind him; he is the firſt-born of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; this hour he is fraught with Gold, as if the grand Elixir were his own: to morrow you ſhall meet him poorer then a Poet; then he is forced to take ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary in the good nature of his Taylor or Shooe-maker, who (though Jews enough) will yet give him Credit perhaps for a Guiney, becauſe after a good hand he payeth well; with this he marcheth to the Ordinary, in hopes to make that two, he looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it, and at twelve in the night, in great diſpair he goeth home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, in his way meeteth with and quarrels the Watch, hath his head broken, and is laid in the Counter to repent till day; now if his Reputation ebbeth ſo, that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50479:22"/>he can have nothing upon Truſt; and his fortune ſo bad, that his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactreſs in the City (who is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly a Merchants wiſe) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help him, becauſe her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band hath the Key of the Caſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>box; he then poſteth to the place of Execution, throws at all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Table, if his Caſt be good he ſweepeth it, if bad, he oweth them all; and if he be a very poor Raſcal, his loving Creditors remit him the ſumm, and kick him down the ſtairs. Upon theſe diſadvantages, do men play that have fortunes: them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may eaſily be ruin'd, (nay, it is forty to one if they are not,) but the others being already up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ground, can fall no low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; he often, when he is idle, maketh his entry <hi>gratis</hi> at the 5th
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50479:22"/>Act of a Play; and there either picketh up a loving Female whom he maketh drunk, and then abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth 2 or 3 Bullies, who drown their cares and ſing the Sun down and up with impious Catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; Oaths are ſo frequent with him, that he can as well not move his Eyes, as leave them; they are Complements to his period, and they make them rounder: thus doth he murther his precious and immortal ſoul, which at laſt he expireth either from a bed of loathſome diſeaſes and rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or from a diſgraceful Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet with common Malefactors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="profession">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:50479:23"/>
               <head>The Virtuoſo</head>
               <p>DId riſe Gloriouſly, like light out of the <hi>Chaos,</hi> and daz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Eyes of the aſtoniſhed world, triumphing with a Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine Gallantry over the impra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable Notions of the Antients; but now he ſeemeth not to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue his advantage with his primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive vigor, which hath diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Fame a little; for whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver treadeth the paths of Virtue, ought always to be in a forward motion, and by equal degrees, as he advanceth in the way, to dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his pace till he cometh to the Goal. The Great Chancellor Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con was the Columbus, who led us to this unknown <hi>America</hi> of new <hi>Philſophy,</hi> ſince him <hi>Carte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:50479:23"/>and <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> have made the greateſt diſcoveries in her Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, to whom we ſhall with all willingneſs yield the Bays, if we conſider the advantages we now enjoy from their labour; for all Precepts, all Notions are given us from above to regulate and direct our Actions; and the beſt of ſpeculations are buried in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion, if they do not produce their due effects; now it is moſt certain, that moſt, or all of the principles of the Paripatetic Philoſophy were <hi>meer Entia Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis, in intellectu tantum,</hi> which now give place to <hi>Entia realia,</hi> to true and beneficial Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; doubtleſs it was the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of a moſt Heroick Virtue, to ſtorm the whole Circle of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Learning, ſo much reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50479:24"/>by Men, though for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> other cauſe then its Antiquity and the perſwaſions they had their Fathers eſteemed it, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> old times they honoured aged Oaks, becauſe they thought ſome God had kept his reſidence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their ſhades. It is admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble how a body made up of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> many jarring and diſagreeing Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (I mean oppoſite opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) ſhould have obtain'd ſo much, and gain'd ſo mighty at Aſcendant over the affections of men of parts enough refined, that they ſhould pronounce him an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, who ſhould dare to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the meaneſt of its Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; bearing it up againſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience which ought to be out general Miſtreſs.</p>
               <p>The Engliſh <hi>Literati</hi> have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50479:24"/>the World with Effects of Induſtry and Ingenuity moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of their cauſes; they have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved the Art of Grinding Glaſſes, which is a great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to Aſtronomy and Sea-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; by the ſtudy of Microgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, and the Anatomy of inſects, they have diſplaied a new Page of the Book of Nature; they have by more exact ſcrutiny into humane bodies, diſcovered the circulation and the ſource of many diſeaſes, and have lately oblig'd us with an experiment of the transfuſion of the blood of one Animal into another, which is never enough to be gratefully admired, though it hath the ill fortune to be little e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed of now, but in enſuing ages, it will certainly be crowned with its due applauſe; for it is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50479:25"/>always ſeen that great Actions are deny'd their Bay's in that age in which they are born, becauſe Envy and prejudicate Malice, (the off-ſprings of the old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent) detract from them. The Hypotheſis of Water, and Air, (the advance of the latter being — in the Air-pump, a Noble me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick invention) are very ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and the inſpection into the Nature of Vegetables, hath much advantaged Man in the ſupport his body will receive from them. Their progreſs in all Phyſical Learning hath generally been great; but upon Chymiſtry par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly they have ſpent much Labour, and Oyl. And here I muſt declare, that though I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour all the ingenious and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious, I cannot be reconcil'd to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50479:25"/>thoſe who are in purſuit of that great Magiſtery of Nature (as they call it) the Philoſophers ſtone; it is wonderful that they ſhould conſume ſo conſiderable a portion of their lives in the ſearch of that which they know not really to be in the Created ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: or if it ſhould exiſt, which hath ſo mean an end as the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gold into the World, which is the efficient cauſe of all ſtriſes, and evils; whoſe converſe the good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void, becauſe it commonly turneth even the ſouls of its votaries in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to its own Hypoſtaſis: how cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly do they macerate themſelves who ſearch for this! how they foment thoſe ſcourges of our lives, Hope, and Fear! each mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute bringeth with it a promiſe of ſucceſs which expiteth <hi>in Fumc;</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:50479:26"/>and at laſt when they are juſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Frontiers of bliſs, and think the next minute to embrace their wiſh'd for Elixit, they find in their Arm onely a <hi>Caput mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum,</hi> a <hi>Terra Damnata,</hi> in which they have buried perhaps their whole fortunes, and the greateſt number of their moſt hopeful years, and all which at laſt ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from the expence, is ſummed up in two, or three moral Corol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries; and they end their days with this Prayer in their mouths,
<q>O ſi praeteritos reparet mihi Jupiter annes.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now, to return to the <hi>Virtuoſo;</hi> when I conſider what ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns of civility we make to theſe ingenious perſons who have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged us ſo much, I can find our coldneſs to have no other cauſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50479:26"/>then what themſelves do give, they ſo readily admitting all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons into their Society, who will pay the Duties of the houſe, though they know not the terms of Philoſophy, make the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, who never ſee the bottom of an affair, judge of all from their weakneſs; they common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertain the company of a Coffee-houſe, with ſome refuſe notions gleaned from the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, which they pronounce as Magiſterially as if they had been ſecretary's to Nature, and diſcourſe as confidently of the harmony of her parts, as a Countrey Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian playeth who never learned his <hi>Gam-ut.</hi> From the imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies of theſe pretenders, this Royal Corporation ſuffereth, when it ought rather to be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50479:27"/>and careſſed by all the Great and Learned for all the great advantages it promiſeth in the future; for it is moſt true, that whoſoever is a good Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher is a good man; becauſe no one looketh into the receſſes of Nature, who is not induced to extoll the Author of it, and ſo gratefully maketh his return for the immenſe favours in ſerving and honouring him who confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them. Thus out of a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal knowledge, a Moral one ſtarts and we ſee Science and Virtue have the ſame Baſis. It is certain, Learning hath no Enemies but the Envious, and Ignorant, and even from theſe evils ſhe reapeth good; for from the detraction of the former, ſhe raiſeth repute, ſince nothing but Virtue is the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50479:27"/>ſubject of Envy, and from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterateneſs of the latter, ſhe hath a benefit too; ſince the praiſes of the unwiſe are reproaches, and whoſoever delighteth in them, wrappeth himſelf in the better half of his Fools-coat; and <hi>E converſo</hi> his reproaches muſt be praiſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="profession">
               <head>The Divine</head>
               <p>HAth the powers of curſing, and abſolving upon Earth; and therefore ought to be reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renc'd as Gods immediate inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Now, though his injuries be many from the diſaffected, yet under theſe great preſſures he ought with the Palme, to lift up
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50479:28"/>his head higheſt; and to exalt his voice like a Trumpet to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain warre againſt all the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions of Vice; every one bendeth his bow to the head, and aims at the white of the Clergy's inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, accuſing them for cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, and looſ-livers, not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how many amongſt them are neither: but grant they were ſo, we ought, as men, to pardon them their errors; and as the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Heaven we ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence them: ſhould we be ſtruck ſo ſurely from above for every little ſinne, as we do one another, our whole ſpecies had before this time been utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and had left the World to be poſſeſs'd by ſenſitive be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; but I fear the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern of theſe pretenders will one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50479:28"/>prove that which taketh not its ſource from a due principle, but a ſenſual end; the deſire of poſſeſſing the Churches revenues; if ſo, oh how impious is their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign! ſurely they that ſerve at the Altar ought to live by it; if they who ſerve Earthly Kings, ought to live gloriouſly according to the dignity of their Lords; then <hi>à fortiori,</hi> they ought to be in all things above the reſt, who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon the Monarch of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and Earth: but there is one thing which would in all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood recover the Church, and that is, if the Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the Nation could be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to enter into Orders; by their Alliance, and Intereſt, they might bulwark themſelves againſt thoſe who would break in upon
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50479:29"/>them, through the mightieſt faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of their Virtue: no one can be too good to attend at the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar: <hi>David</hi> was King and Prieſt, and ſo were all his ſucceſſors in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and it was imputed to the Jews for ſin, that they choſe their Prieſts out of the meaneſt of the people; for their perſons being held in contempt by thoſe who were their equals before; their Office comes to be ſo too, and the beſt parts alſo ſuffer when clouded with poverty.</p>
               <q>Raro in tenui facundia panno.</q>
               <p>It is true, that Heaven lately ſhewed its diſpleaſure to our Church, and ſeated Forreigners in its fatteſt Sees; yet it was ſaid to them, as to the Iſraelites when
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50479:29"/>they went to poſſeſs <hi>Canaan,</hi> I ſend you up to poſſeſs the Land of the <hi>Anakim,</hi> not for your own Righteouſneſs, (for you are a ſtiffe-necked people) but to ſcourge the Nations which enjoy it. But now we may plainly ſee how great the concern of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is for the Church, ſince the Eccleſiaſtical and politick Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are ſo united, that they both fall, and both riſe together; Many now ſhoot at her founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but I hope ſhe is built upon <hi>Zion</hi> which cannot be moved. The points of Toleration and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion have been ſo thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcuſs'd, that here I need but mention their names, onely I muſt ſay, I ſhould be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to ſee either of them ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in this Kingdom. Now
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50479:30"/>the Churchmen ought rather <hi>Magna vivere</hi> then <hi>Magna loqui,</hi> and to ſhew by their own practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that the Precepts which they give may be eaſily obeyed. The fat Bulls of <hi>Baſan</hi> have prevail'd now; but the Almighty hath one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly crowned them with ſucceſs, to make them fall nobler Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to his wrath.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="profession">
               <head>The Phyſitian</head>
               <p>IS to the body what the Divine is to the ſoul, though he doth not adminiſter his province with a parallel integrity; ſince his Knowledge is increaſed, Diſeaſes are ſo too; and our bodies by his applications are become leſs robuſt, and vigorous; for by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50479:30"/>on them, our natural heat and radical humours are impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which were our ſupports; and not ſeldome, the very remedy of one Malady is the cauſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but not onely from this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural cauſe, but a more inhumane one, reſulteth as great an evil; for to ſwell his own profit, he often prolongeth the Agonies, the Miſeries of his poor Patient, making himſelf ſeem to him a greater diſtemper then that he is already travailed with. From thoſe dry bones, which none who paſſe by, can think could live, he will extract a lively and ſparkling Eſſence to himſelf, and he will draw ſweetneſs from the moſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified Carcaſſe, his <hi>Recipe</hi> whoſe barbarous Character fully ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his — manners) produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50479:31"/>two Pieces to himſelf; then if you ſhould recover, (which is more the effect of Providence then his Care,) the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or Chirurgeon giveth with a cruel Bill, the lately cicatrized wound, a new gaſh; he viſiteth you as long as the pulſe of your Purſe beateth high; but when he findeth it to decline, then, he ſaith, you grow ſo well that you need not his Art; or your diſeaſe is ſo deſperate, that it cannot aſſiſt you; his thoughts of God are not ſo as they ought to be; for by his ſo frequently view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the works of Nature, he is apt to miſapply and attribute too much to ſecond Cauſes. He adoreth that great principle of Nature, Self-preſervation, but neglecteth that as great one of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50479:31"/>Chriſtianity, to preſerve his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; nay rather like a <hi>Cannibal,</hi> he preyeth upon him: though I very much honour this profeſſion, yet I muſt not the abuſes of it; though it be very neceſſary, yet the neglects, and the ill ends of the profeſſors of it, render it often dangerous: for it is moſt certain, that they not ſeldome by their Clothes do transferre the diſeaſe of one, to the other; and it is as ſure that many ſuffer by their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying Medicines to diſeaſes, which plain Care, or Nature would work off. If his Fees were more moderate, the Patient would receive a greater advantage, and himſelfe no detriment; for now, by the exceſs of them, the ſick perſon cannot ſee him above once in a day, and there being ſo
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50479:32"/>many critical minutes in a diſeaſe, it is impoſſible he ſhould preſcribe for them in his abſence. Thus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the inferior ſort of the Nation will enjoy a benefit; for many who are loſt for want of advice, are able to give a Crown, who cannot afford a Guinny: it is in fine, a profeſſion, which employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the induſtry and ſtudy of its Profeſſors, and chargeth them with the greateſt duties and care, and therefore ought to be moſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced if it impoſe not too much upon the World.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="profession">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:50479:32"/>
               <head>The Lawyer.</head>
               <p>FRom <hi>Adam</hi> to the Flood, the Law of Nature onely reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but, when wickedneſſes increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the ſurface of the earth, God laid his commands againſt Murther and Bloud, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards as the age degenerated Laws increaſed, and became an <hi>Aſylum</hi> to the Good, and a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to the Bad. Since the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of brethren is rare, becauſe every man preferreth his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, Law is appointed for the preſervation of the world; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the approaches to it, ought to be eaſie, for if a Sanctuary be locked, of what advantage is it to that miſerable man who flieth to its protection: the Law which
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50479:33"/>God gave to his peculiar people, which he often called <hi>ſtiff-neck'd</hi> and perverſe, was compriſed within the narrow compaſs of two Tables; and this he thought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to bridle their greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitancies; the Twelve Tables, nay the Roman or Civil Law it ſelf governed a Nation the moſt Great, moſt Glorious, and moſt Adventrous in the World; which without the impertinent, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeſted gloſſes of <hi>Bartolus</hi> and <hi>Baldus,</hi> and others, is of very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle volume; But we of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are now expoſed by what ſhould be our refuge; devoured by what ſhould be our guard; the Rules of our Law growing into ſo monſtrous a body, that like the famed Dragon, they devour daily a conſiderable Member of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50479:33"/>the Virgin juſtice. Every Term bringeth forth a collection of new Reports; and every Judgement ſoweth the ſeed of a new ſtrife; betwixt the Pleaders and the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torneys, the Prize which the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties contend for is ſhared; the latter of which, is a generation of men ſo Magiſterial where they live, and ſo oppreſſing, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, ſo numerous, that at laſt, with the too much injur'd Client, they will devour the Lawyer too: who certainly hath the ſame ground to preferr a Bill in Parliament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, for invading his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, as the Phyſician had againſt the Apothecary; how unhappy are ſince we under the wings of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended juſtice all enormities are committed! She now like a rich Heireſs is bought and ſold, and that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50479:34"/>which ſhould oppoſe deceit, is it ſelf now become the greateſt, ſo that <hi>Photinus</hi>'s principle in <hi>Lucan</hi> ſeemeth to be the Lawyer's.</p>
               <q>Jus, &amp; fas multos faciunt Ptolemae nocentes.</q>
               <p>The poor Country-man when with his Hat in his hand, he hath intreated his Councellour to let him buy his miſery, is after two or three years attendance, and the charge of witneſſes and jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, diſmiſſed with the loſs of his cauſe, (ſo that it may be ſaid, the Law, like <hi>Rome</hi> in her gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, <hi>ſuis ipſa viribus ruit,</hi>) and after a ſeeming trouble is told, that his own miſtaken inſtructions were the ruine of his affair. But thoſe who have long been toſſed in theſe troubleſome waters find that the ſafeſt way to an Haven
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:50479:34"/>is to Fee his Antagoniſt's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, as well as his own; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyances which we make now are ſcarce contained in many skins of Parchment; and often for the miſtake of one word, the whole fabrique is ruin'd, though it be evidently contrary to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Conveyer. Though theſe days are more adorn'd with Gold; yet thoſe nearer the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Conqueſt, and before it, more reſembled the Golden ones. For then; a few Rhithmes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by an honeſt well mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Bard, ſerved to paſs away the greateſt poſſeſſions: the hearts of men were ſure more honeſt, and their deſigns more honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, when it was enough to write.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:50479:35"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I give this Lond from me, and mine,</l>
                     <l>To thee, and thine: —</l>
                     <l>Witneſs</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Meg, Maud,</hi> and Margery,</l>
                     <l>And my young Son <hi>Harry.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And to ſhew this is in ſooth,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> bite this green wax with my Tooth.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>The ways to prevent ſuits were to appoint a Regiſter in every County, where the Eſtates of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Lord and Freeholder ſhould be entred, that ſo the Purchaſer may underſtand for what he traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiqueth.</p>
               <p>It would alſo prove much more eaſie for all, if the Parliament would enact that a ſumm ſhould be difaulked from the ordinary Fees of the Lawyer, and that no cauſe ſhould depend in any
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:50479:35"/>Court above a time which they ſhould praefix; this would very much remedy the dilatorineſs of their Proceſſes: It rouſeth my ſpleen to ſee men ſo infatuated, and ſo prone to gratifie revenge, that they will ruine themſelves to advance people, many of whom are ſo great ſtrangers to fence, if diverted from the paths they run in, that if one deſireth to be reſolved of the reaſon of a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or decree, they tell you it is according to their Books; by which, doubtleſs, they are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently very much impoſed on. They receive the <hi>placita</hi> of their Sages with greater reverence then the Auncients did their Oracles, which they thought were inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from Heaven; and attribute a greater infalibility to them then
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:50479:36"/>thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> perſwaſion in Eccleſiaſtick affairs to the Pope; forgetting that as humane, they may err in their opinions; ſetting them up above experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, from which <hi>Oſbourne</hi> ſaid truly, King <hi>Charles</hi> received bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Precepts then his Father from <hi>Buchanan.</hi> In fine, we may know them to be the ſoul of diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and rapine; becauſe like the iſſue of the Dragon's teeth ſown by <hi>Cadmus,</hi> they begin to bite and embroile the Nation as ſoon as they tread her Stage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="profession">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:50479:36"/>
               <head>The Poet</head>
               <p>VErſe to the brave, is like the Trumpet to the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour: it animates them to greater exploits.
<note n="*" place="margin">Ode Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darique inſcribed the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</note> Mr. <hi>Cowley</hi> declareth its great uſe in the following Stanza.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Not winds to Voyagers at Sea,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Not ſhowers to Earth more neceſſary be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(Heavens vital ſeed caſt on the womb of earth</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To give the fruitful year a birth)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then Verſe to Vertue, which can do</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Midwiſ's office, and the Nurſes too;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It feedeth it ſtrongly, and it cloaths it gay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And when it dies, with comely pride</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Embalmes it, and erects a Pyramid.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That never will decay</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Till Heaven it ſelf ſhall melt away,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And nought behind it ſtay.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:50479:37"/>
It is reported of <hi>Alexander,</hi> that in all his expeditions he made <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> his companion; and I verily ſuppoſe the Panegyricks of thoſe dead <hi>Heroes</hi> inſpired him with the briskeſt thoughts of emulation. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etry hath been Reverenced in all ages ſince the very firſt dawn of knowledge; which reſpect hath cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly had its ſource from the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles delivering of their anſwers, and the ancient Philoſophers ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth their opinions in Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The high ſentiments which the Latines entertain for it, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by their giving the Profeſſors of it the honourable Title of <hi>Vates.</hi> The Bards and Chroniclers in the Iſles of <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> have been in former times even ador'd for the Ballads in which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll'd the Deeds of their forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:50479:37"/>and ſince the ages have been refined, doubtleſs, <hi>England</hi> hath produced thoſe, who in this way have equall'd moſt of the Antients: and exceeded all the Moderns. <hi>Chaucer</hi> roſe like the morning Starr of Wit, out of thoſe black miſts of ignorance; ſince him, <hi>Spencer</hi> may deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly challenge the Crown; for though he may ſeem blameable in not obſerving <hi>decorum</hi> in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces enough, and in too much, in the whole, countenancing Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>errantry; yet the eaſie ſimilitudes, the natural Pourtraicts, the ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined and ſublimated fancies with which he hath ſo beſtudded every Canto of his ſubject will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily reach him the Guerdon; and though fome may object to him that his Language is harſh and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquated;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:50479:38"/>yet his deſign was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; to ſhew us that our language was expreſſive enough of our own ſentiments; and to upbraid thoſe who have indenizon'd ſuch num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of forreign words; ſince in this way ſo many have excell'd, that we can give the Crown to no one, but the reſt muſt be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly injured: yet they muſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me if I tell them that they ſeem to have degenerated by turning their ſtiles to light and inſignificant Sonnets, and ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous Burleſque, and offenſive doggrel; which laſt way of Drol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery hath ſo much obtain'd now, that they doubt not to abuſe all ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things in it; nay even to make the lofty expreſſions of the Prince of Poets to ſeem ridiculous. They have not onely done this but ſome
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:50479:38"/>have turn'd that which us'd to charme our thoughtful heads, and to perſwade our diſtemper'd ſpirits into gentle ſlumbers, by ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and natural ſoftneſs, into a rough Miſtery and Art; they ſtrive to bring wit, which is of ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known a Nature, that like the wind no one knoweth whence it is, under logical Notions; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing ſyllogiſtically and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the world with Volumes of what is impertinent to it; that they may advance their own names, ſo turning our delight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to trouble. 'Tis a pity that men of theſe abilities ſhould not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble ſome of thoſe great ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects which our Nation yieldeth: but ſhould ſpend their time in praiſing an Eye, or Feature, which they may ſee exceeded at
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:50479:39"/>any Countrey Wake. By this it is more evident that we have deviated from thoſe paths which did lead our Anceſtors to fame, and are become ſo effeminate, that like <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> we ſpin amongſt the Women, who by their Artifices have ſo wholly gain'd us, that we ſpeak or think of nothing elſe; as commonly through our whole Malady thoſe objects detain our thoughts moſt, which affected them at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it, and were its cauſes, ſince the ſtage which uſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent general vices is come to reflect on particulars; it ſelf, whilſt it injureth the reputation of any one, becometh the greateſt vice. <hi>Momus</hi> is not allowed to ſpeak of all at all times. Since all men are naturally prone to ill, whoever
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:50479:39"/>is not purg'd himſelf, cannot ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe another.</p>
               <p>By theſe ways no Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is wrought, but great animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities ariſe. They who have fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties this way, ought to employ them in ſupporting the Pyramids of ancient virtue, or building new ones to it. Since the Sword defends the Pen, it ought to adorn the ſword; ſince the Lawrels of the brave and valorous do defend the Muſes from the Thunder of their Eenemies, and make them enjoy, in all tranquility, the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Groves, and refreſhing Rills of their <hi>Parnaſſus;</hi> they ought in grateful layes to tranſmit the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements of ſo great Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors to all poſterity.</p>
               <q>Vivitur ingenio Caetera mortis erunt.</q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="gender">
            <pb facs="tcp:50479:40"/>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:50479:40"/>
            <head>Woman,</head>
            <p>THough Man was made Lord over all beings, and his Empire ſtretch'd it ſelf over the whole Globe, though his Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al redence was in a place which adminiſtred all things to his pleaſure, and ſeem'd to be the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement and quinteſſence of the Univerſe; yet he thought his enjoyments imperfect, till he had an help correſpondent to his affections, and a fit object for thoſe faculties with which he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed. For this cauſe therefore, woman was Created out of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who ſeemeth to have been his beſt part; and like that ſmall eſſence which Chymiſts extract out of a large, and maſſive Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance:
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:50479:41"/>therefore Man having by his converſe with the cauſes of all things gathered knowledge, is ſenſible of what they of this Sex are capable; and fearing leſt they ſhould Rival him in his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, impoſeth on them, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading them that their faculties are not receptive of Arts, and rough Virtues; and by this ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem conſineth them by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of a narrow Province, bounded by the walls of their Court, and Garden, whilſt he is exercis'd in the Nobler affairs of the Court and Schools, when it is clear that their inclinations are better then his, and their reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons greater: for it is obſerv'd, they are generally more Virtuous and Devout then we; and when they do deviate to Vice, they are more
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:50479:41"/>hardned and perſevering in it; the great actions in which they have born a part, ſpeaketh the excellency of their Natures. The Amazons (if we believe ſtory) have excell'd in Warr. To <hi>Sap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho</hi> we owe the invention of the ſweeteſt kind of Verſe in Lirique Poetry. <hi>Lucretia</hi> by her reſolution has rais'd her ſelf a deathleſs Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument. And <hi>Judith</hi> in Sacred Writ is remembred with great Glory. All theſe examples ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the greatneſs of their parts; which while they do not employ, but are content to forgoe all the pleaſures with which knowledge would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them; they ſeem to have made a Salique Law to bind them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Did they but conſider what an aſcendant they have over the ſouls of men, and that though
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:50479:42"/>they were the ſource of all our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, we ſhould ſtill adore them: as alſo thoſe great advantages out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dull, and phlegmatique conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions own from the purifying flames of Love: they would exert their powers, and launch out of thoſe dark Regions of ignorance in which they ſleep, into the bright and Sunny Countreys of Knowledge. I offer this, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> encourage them to rebel againſt Man, whom God hath made the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> head; but to adviſe them to ſerve the World under ſome other No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Character, and not onely to devote themſelves to the uſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Generation. In no Countrey ſo many of this fair Sex, as in <hi>England</hi> exceed in Beauty and Wit. The firſt of which, the Temperateneſs of our Climate does much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:50479:42"/>which is in ſo juſt a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt heat and cold, that it injoyeth the benefits of both, and feeleth the inconveniencies of neither. If we go towards the <hi>South,</hi> we find the People ſtill a degree more ſwarthy; if towards the <hi>North,</hi> more brawny and groſs; built to receive the rude aſſaults the winds breed there, though of a complexion general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clear enough; that they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous above thoſe of other Countreys is evident from their prudent management of Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomical affairs, for on them with us they all relie; which is a great Truſt, ſince the welfare of the State depends upon the health of its Members; the reaſon of this is, the ſo frequent and familiar converſe they are allow'd with
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:50479:43"/>men within the bounds of Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, which, no people, the <hi>French</hi> excepted, admits of to ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. And certainly in their ſo great ſtrictneſs to this Sex, the <hi>Italians</hi> (thoſe grand Maſters of Pollticks) do very much err. For beſides the injuſtice they act in depriving them of that liberty which God, and Nature allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them; it is impoſſible they ſhould ever become more virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous by being conſin'd to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly of a Cloyſter which to deceive the idle hours, muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge and adminiſter looſe thoughts, which with God are equivalent with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; when, it they converſed in the world, they might improve themſelves in Knowledge; and the diverſions they would receive from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:50479:43"/>of others, would keep them from thinking ill ſo frequently; and Modeſty from acting it. And it is moſt ſure, that if ever they can free themſelves from thoſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Fetters of miſtaken Devotion; the Flames which have been ſo long ſmother'd, will burſt out with ſuch an impetuoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and violence, that they will devour all inclinations to Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and Virtue, and will never be extinguiſh'd in the deepeſt Abyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of carnal enjoyments.</p>
            <div type="position">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:50479:44"/>
               <head>The Maid</head>
               <p>IS Natures Richeſt Cabinet lock'd; who yet ardently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to diſplay thoſe Glories ſhe containeth, and thinketh ſhe hath not the perfect enjoyment of them, if not communicated; when ſhe hath attain'd to the uſe of her Organs of Speech, the firſt word ſhe uttereth after Dad, and Mam, is Husband; who from that time reigneth in her thoughts ſo much that ſhe maketh it her chief end to captivate him; but if her Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> have ſo little care of her as to let her paſs her younger years ſingle rather than to hang longer on the Tree, the too ripe fruit will fall to any man. She, like an expert General, chooſeth rather to uſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:50479:44"/>ſtratagem in ſtorming a Fort, then wholly to rely upon her ſtrength, be it never ſo great; for I never ſaw that Woman, how fair ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that was not guilty of thoſe innocent frauds of a patch, or waſh, hoping from them for great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er acceſſions of Beauty. In her diſcourſe ſhe commonly traduces the reſt of her Sex, and tacitely giveth a riſe to applaud her ſelf, which, (though ſhe deſerveth not) you muſt do with the greateſt of your powers; for in the ſtate of Love, as well as in the civil one, he is the beſt Politician who can beſt diſſemble. You cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine what near approaches you make to her affections by theſe ways, and how really ſhe is taken with you, though you deſcribe her by all the impoſſibilities of Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try:
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:50479:45"/>when ſhe might ſoon be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceived; would ſhe with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Eye conſult her Glaſſes. But yet this Humour, ingraffed in her Nature (which certainly proceeds from the want of a true uſe of her reaſon,) if it ſeemeth to increaſe with her age; for even thoſe whom many years have ſeen Virgins, are more vain then the younger ones; and are not to be convinc'd, but that the ſame lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre inhabiteth their eyes, which reſided in them 30 years before. Hence it is that you ſee them ſo ſollicitous to ſill up thoſe furrows which time hath plowed, and to ſupply the places of thoſe Teeth which years have ruin'd, with ſorreign ones, and to burniſh thoſe eyes which Sixty Suns have dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Her diſcourſe is repleniſh'd
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:50479:45"/>with the Hiſtories of thoſe ſhe might have had; what proper men ſhe refuſed, and upon what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſhe ſlighted them; and in the concluſion, ſhe will torment your ears with a doleful Sonnet, or heart-melting direful addreſs, compoſed by ſome of her croſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd Lovers, who flouriſh'd in Poetry above halfe a Century be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ben Johnſon.</hi> She now, (like the old worn Sinner when his powers have left him,) voweth practical Chaſtity, though her thoughts often tranſgreſs, and run into a ſpeculative obſcenity. She commonly is at enmity with her elder Brothers wife, who ſeemeth to grudge her her Annuity; but now ſhe ſerveth for no other uſe but to careſs thoſe Babies to whom ſhe is a great Aunt; and to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:50479:46"/>give her young Neices inſtruction; for their behaviour when they are wooed. To mention all her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinence, were a labour as end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs as her own diſcourſe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as troubleſome; I ſhall therefore Land you upon a new Scene, and preſent her to your view in the ſtate of Matrimony.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="position">
               <head>The Wife.</head>
               <p>SInce the impertinencies of the Maid alwayes continue, and grow up in the Wife, if ſhe be not guided by a natural prudence, he who paints one of them giveth you the full draught of the other: I think it therefore not extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſique to my Province to lay down ſome rules for the choice of a
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:50479:46"/>Wife; in which great circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ought to be uſed, ſince by this Union a man either builds his happineſs, or miſery during life. If my Friend prove falſe, I can ſtrike a League with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; if my Servant be unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, I can change him; but though my Wife prove ſo, ſhe muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main mine. Matrimony is a <hi>Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Knot, which no <hi>Alexander</hi> can cut. He who intends to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a double ſtate ought not to chooſe a Woman only for her Pedigree; if other circumſtances are wanting, eſpecially Virtue, his Election is lame; for what was it at firſt that ennobled her Line but that? and if that Pillar fail, her Eſcucheon muſt needs fall. If her Relations are poor, nothing can fall more unhappily to him,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:50479:47"/>for ſhe will ſtill draw them to be warmed at his fire: Like the Courtier who is not ſatisfied to beek himſelf only in the Sun-ſhine of his Soveraign's favour, but will alſo bring his Kindred within the warmth of his raies; ſo that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever matches here, eſpouſeth not one, but a whole Family. When the Head of the houſe fals, his dependants by conſequence partake of his fortune, and they certainly muſt be very numerous; the Setting-ſun caſts the longeſt ſhadow. Her pride alſo will make the blood of her Children run high, which will be their great unhappineſs, when they muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the univerſal allay of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty. What can be more deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picable than a Title without the ſupport of an Eſtate? a mans ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:50479:47"/>bids him ſoar to high things, his want forces him to the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt actions: he is, like a bird up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wing, to mount whilſt a leaden Plummet tied to his Leg keeps him down.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let not Beauty alone allure any man without internal, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal endowments: She who can boaſt nothing but good outward features, is like an houſe adorned without with various Pillars, and Pillaſters of ſeveral Orders, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Cornices, and neat Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings; but within naked, and without either Orchard, Garden, or Wood: this may treat your eye a while, but it neither ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſters to the delight of your mind, nor the neceſſities of your body. She will be a Magnet to draw as well the noble Steel to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:50479:48"/>your houſe as the ignobler Iron; moſt comers inquire for you, but be aſſured their viſit is to my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. No Woman's virtue in the World (if young) can be ſo ſtrong a Fort to her, but it may be rendered to the perpetual ſhowers of flatterie, and comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which play upon it. If ſhe yield to a noble conquerour, you have the honour to march out with your horns in your pocket and flying colours, but never hope to be re-inſtated in the place you had in her breaſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let not Riches alone draw any man; for thus he enſlaves himſelf, firſt to the Gold, and then to the imperious humour of one he hates; who ſtill plagues him with repeating that acceſſion his fortunes received by her,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:50479:48"/>though ſhe commonly hath the chief hand in ſpending it: who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever then ſtands thus, muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs himſelf to be a ſlave, though bound with a golden Chain, and that the fettered Captive in the deepeſt Dungeon is more free than he, becauſe however his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is ſecured, he reſerves the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of his mind to himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</p>
               <p>Aim not too much at an Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs, for her defects are notable, and many, Nature commonly ſending her into the world rude and unfiniſhed, becauſe ſhe ſees Fortune ſtanding ready at her En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to poliſh and adorn her with her gifts; in which the Juſtice of Heaven in the diſtribution of bleſſings to men is evident, ſince all Graces never meet in one
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:50479:49"/>Creature, but every one hath ſomething different which renders it agreeable to the reſt: But if your ſtarrs ſeem to direct you this way, you muſt not, (nor truly can you) addreſs to her in the uſual way; for would it not be very groſs to aſſure one who is crooked, lame, thin-faced, il-eyed, that ſhe is fair, beautifull and alluring, but you muſt bid fair for her to thoſe who menage her (yet within compaſs, if you would be a ſaver by your Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, for ſhe is commonly a moſt extravagant ſpender) and then you are ſure to ſucceed, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if ſhe be in the hands of a mercenary Father-in-law.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Nor a let a quick Wit, a good aſſurance, a good mien, nor the additions of ſinging, playing,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:50479:49"/>dancing be motives to affection, for they enhance not her value more, but rather make her higher. Whoever hath one, or all of theſe, and wants Virtue, is like a body well ſhaped, yet without an arm, a leg, or eye. But ſince we may not hope to find all theſe acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents centred in one Subject, more than all Arts and Sciences in one Brain: Virtue is to be choſen naked, before all the other gaily dreſſed and embroidered. This fair creature is a portion of her ſell; 'tis ſhe who faſtens a bleſſing to all her Husbands undertakings; 'tis ſhe who though ſhe brings not Riches, yet gathers them; 'tis ſhe who preſents him with fair and chaſt Children to adorn his Table, and ſupport his age; 'tis ſhe who giveth her King loyal Subjects,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:50479:50"/>and her Country good and juſt Patriots; 'tis ſhe who in her Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved's abſence ſhuts her gates to all forreigners, and at his return recreates, and careſſes him with chaſte embraces, and heals him with balmy kiſſes; 'tis ſhe who by her prudence ſills his Granaries within, whilſt he ſupplies her from without; 'tis ſhe who feeds the Poor, and cloaths the Naked; 'tis ſhe who loves his friends, and hates not, but prayes the converſion of his enemies; 'tis her breaſt which receives his cares, and her lips give him words of joy</p>
               <p>Let no one chooſe one deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (if he can avoid it) for it is obſerved the mind is alwayes of the ſame ſhape. A good Inn hath very ſeldome a bad Sign-poſt. Nature never impreſſes an ill mark
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:50479:50"/>upon her good pieces. This An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity knew, when it ſaid, <hi>Cave ſis ex eo quam Natura ſigillaverit.</hi> Loſe not any other material cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance in one, for another that is fairer; for the firſt thing a man neglects in his Wife is her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. If it be thought convenient let her be paſt the Small-pox, for then one ſeeth the worſt of her. Let her be well-ſhaped, for the neateſt built Ship ſails beſt. Above all let her be of the ſame faith with her Husband; for how can they concurr in the menage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their affairs, who diſagree in the way of worſhiping their God? If to virtue Heaven will add <hi>externa bona,</hi> outward goods, be thankful: if it doth not, be not too ſollicitous to obtain them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="position">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:50479:51"/>
               <head>The Widow,</head>
               <p>EIther hoping for better for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, if her Husband hath been bad, or if good, deſiring to repeat thoſe pleaſures he hath been author of to her, is alwaies ready to hold out her hand for new manacles. The Arts by which ſhe menageth her deſignes are theſe: ſhe giveth out her ſums to be very great, her demeaſns large, and her years few, well knowing that no man of fortunes will come on unleſs upon one of theſe accounts. The ſame of theſe draws perhaps a Lord to her, who proteſts by her eyes, an Oath with him moſt ſacred, that he loves and honours her above all the world, that ſhe alone diſpoſeth his
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:50479:51"/>fate, that it is in her breaſt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him the happieſt, or moſt miſerable of men; he extols a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion which her waſhes gave, and ſwears he adores her eye as radiant, which perhaps is blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot; He tells her it ſends forth darts, which like to the <hi>Pelian</hi> Spear, have the power of killing, but like it too, it ought to exerciſe that of reviving: How long! how long (Madam ſaith he) is it your pleaſure I ſhall continue in theſe torments! I were happy might I fall a victim to your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for the glorie of the action would ſweeten the agonies, and convulſions of my death! But oh! let me not live only to yield my heart a prey to keen and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting Vultures! But when by theſe falſe wayes he hath drawn
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:50479:52"/>the weak Creature to an aſſent, and finding the baggs not to be of that Volume which he expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, his love vaniſheth, and he leaves her in thoſe real Extaſies which before he feigned.</p>
               <p>This amour is ſucceeded per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by that of the powdred Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, who profeſſes and vows to the ſame degree, if not higher; He ſaith all that <hi>Oroondates</hi> could to <hi>Statira,</hi> or <hi>Celadon</hi> to <hi>Aſtrea,</hi> or <hi>Zanger</hi> to the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Queen, ſuperadding, that if the World were his own, he ſhould not have the confidence to ask her to be Empreſs of it, ſince it would be ſo far below her merit: but when he alſo like a valiant Chevalier hath gained the Caſtle, and finding the Outworks not worth the holding, he marcheth
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:50479:52"/>off with whole vollies of Oathes, curſing his hard fortunes.</p>
               <p>Now after theſe Ambaſſadors of Love, and many more of the ſame Mould have had their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diences of Congee, ſhe grows more ſubtle, and ſo leſs credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and now undeceived, ſhe finds her Eyes have not half that luſtre which her Gold hath, and that that, not ſhe hath been their <hi>Diana.</hi> Being then thus deluded, ſhe grows deſperate, and is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to embrace the firſt who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers himſelf; Now he, (perhaps a younger brother) who before went no farther than the drawing-Room, or Antichamber, is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into her Cabinet, and is a jewel ſhe is ſure no body will envy her, and therefore proceeds more freely; and it is a very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:50479:53"/>Scene to behold their carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. He reſolves thus with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By Heavens I'll tell her boldly it is ſhe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi> Why ſhould ſhe ſham'd or angry be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To be belov'd of me?</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <bibl>Mr. Cowley.</bibl>
               <p>His way is compendious, he tells her he cannot ſay much, but Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him he loveth her, and if ſhe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth him, why ſhould they not make a match of it. And by this brisk addreſs, (which is certainly more manly and becoming than the other) he carrieth the Prize, and maketh as good uſe of it. Thus the Widow imitates that Fiſherman, who having baited his hook well, angles all day in hopes of a Salmon, but at laſt he catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Trout, which though it may
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:50479:53"/>not ſatisfie his avarice ſo well, yet it doth his appetite.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <head>
               <hi>The Life of</hi> Theodatus.</head>
            <p>I Shall not much illuſtrate my Subject in laying before you the large Table of <hi>Theodatus</hi>'s An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors; Let it ſuffice to acquaint you that he was well deſcended; nor will I give you the time of his Birth, or any long relations of his Country (you may fancie him a Citizen of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia,</hi> or <hi>Nova-At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantis,</hi>) ſince the only deſign of this Eſſay is to preſent in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the <hi>Idea</hi> of an exactly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed Gentleman. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore trace him through every Stage of his Life, and begin at his
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:50479:54"/>firſt years, when he laid the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of his future glories.</p>
            <p>Know then, that at the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed years he was ſent to School, and there proceeded in the ſame method with the reſt of his Country, till he had attained to a good knowledge in the Latin and Greek Tongues; from whence about the fourteenth year of his age he was removed to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, where he with a great deal of pleaſure, and no leſs ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous induſtry addreſſed himſelf to the Muſes; well knowing, that their favours, as well as thoſe of other Miſtreſſes, were not to be obtained but by many and hard ſervices. According to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the place he began his ſtudies in Philoſophy, he ſoon knew the moſt knotty maximes,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:50479:54"/>and unriddled the greateſt So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſmes, and Subtleties of Logick; he had conſidered, and laid up all the precepts of the Moraliſts, he was acquainted with all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Phyſicks, and had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended all thoſe notions of the Metaphyſician, which he could adjuſt to the Rule of Right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. When he had throughly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the natures of all theſe, he found that they were ſine Idea's, that they commended the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity of the ancient Schools and Porch; that perhaps they might frame his head to diſcourſe or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue plauſibles, but that they were too ſpeculative to be uſeful to him in the neceſſities and emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies of life: therefore he left off to intend thoſe ſtudies as he was wont, (yet he did not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:50479:55"/>lay them aſide) and applied himſelf to Hiſtory, and the moſt uſeful parts of Mathematicks, as Geometry, and thoſe two main Pillars of Hiſtory, Chronologie and Geography; he knew that from theſe noble Records he might gain uſeful Rules of living, and not ſuch as the Ethicks of the Philoſophers give upon truſt, but ſuch as have been confirmed by many great examples; that he might here ſee the ſeveral ends of Virtue and Vice, the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the one, and the infamy of the other; he might here read the praiſes of heroick and juſt <hi>Cato</hi>'s, and view the Monuments built to their Memories; and here behold the misfortunes and fates of ambitious <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s and <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey</hi>'s, the Panegyricks of chaſt and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:50479:55"/>virtuous <hi>Lucretia</hi>'s, and the infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of lacivious and wanton <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi>'s; here the redoubted actions of thoſe mighty ſouls who have fought in their Countries defence, and fallen victims in ſecuring its Altars and Gods will make him emulous, and raiſe him to affect equal attempts, whilſt the ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of thoſe who have invaded the rights of others, maketh him to deteſt their practices; here he might ſee that truth would exert her ſelf, and that thoſe who have ſuffered unjuſtly would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged: In fine he might ſee Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue crowned, and Vice puniſhed. Now what greater argument or motive can there be than this, to embrace the one, and abhorr the other?</p>
            <p>From Mathematicks he learnt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:50479:56"/>that all bodies had longitude, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and profundity, that the two firſt qualities were obvious to every eye, but the latter was only to be ſeen by ſearch, which he applied himſelf to, and would never be ſatisfied till he had learnt to value every thing as it really was, and not as what it ſeemed to be; he, like other men, was not contented with a Probleme which ſhewed him ſuch a thing was, but looked for Theoremes, which told him how, and why: In ſine, he found ſuch demonſtrations in this Learning, that he could never be ſatisfied till he had the ſame in every thing, which he gained by examining its privateſt receſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and corners; ſo by this means he became ſo acquainted with the conſtitution of all things, that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:50479:56"/>only Nature her ſelf could be more ſo. Having remained here till about the 18th year of his age, where his amiable mien and generous carriage had gained him the applauſe of all: he paſſes to the Colleges of the Law to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint himſelf with the ſanctions and conſtitutions of his own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; being ſatisfied that no man could ſerve the Body Politick under any Character unleſs he fully underſtood its humours and complexions. He ſixed himſelf cloſely to theſe ſtudies, (though he did not neglect the healthful exerciſes of his body) and about the 22th year of his age he attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a full knowledge of them. At this time he left his Native Country, and paſſed into thoſe forreign parts which were moſt
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:50479:57"/>famed for Civility, Arts and Arms; and here he did not, as the youth of his time, paſs curſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily through a Country, and gaze only upon its Steeples, and fine Houſes, but like the Wiſe and Eloquent <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <bibl>Hom. Odyſſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>He of each Country had the Cities ſeen,</l>
               <l>And understood the Manners of her Men.</l>
            </q>
            <p>He made uſeful remarques upon their Laws and Cuſtomes, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to what ſtudies they were moſt addicted, how they were provided and ſcituated for Warr and Peace, how they ſtood affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to their Neighbours; he
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:50479:57"/>ſearched into their Military Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, their way of Training and Exerciſing their Souldiery, and their Arts of fortifying Towns, Citadels, and Caſtles; he got an acquaintance with the chief States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the learnedſt in all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions in all Countries through which he travailed, and if he could, he made himſelf known to their ſeveral Princes, and when he thought fit, he ſettled a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with moſt of theſe; he made himſelf Maſter of all thoſe Languages which his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try affected; he marked the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of every Coaſt, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved their way of Complement, and Addreſs, their method in bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and their proceedings in Juſtice; there was nothing which
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:50479:58"/>could adorn his mind that he paſſ'd. Thus fraught with all manner of knowledge about his 25th year he returned, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with their admiration, the love of all his Country-men.</p>
            <p>He never enterprized any thing in which that excellent prudence did not ſhew it ſelf, which had taught him to conſult well, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate maturely, to judge and determine rightly, to conduct and execute reſolutely. He knew this virtue was the ſquare and rule of all affaires, and the only guide to living well: He uſed to ſay, ſhe was with reaſon enthroned above all the other Virtues, and that the Scepter which ſhe ſwayed as their Empreſs did of right belong to her: for without her govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:50479:58"/>Juſtice her ſelf might be miſapplyed, and become dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to her Clients; Fortitude would be no more then a brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Valour, and the ſtrong man would kill and ſlay without the conſideration of a good Cauſe, and Temperance might degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into a ſuperſtitious forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of all ſuſtenance, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſupport, and ſo make the practiſer of it acceſſary to his own ruine, by her we know what, to chooſe as good, and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for life, and what to reject as ſuperfluous and hurtful to it; by her we have the pleaſure to be aſſured that we have not failed in the right uſing of the means, however our buſineſs may ſucceed ill. He would never judge of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:50479:59"/>any thing by its ſucceſs, ſince he ſaw the beſt men unfortunate, and the worſt rewarded: He would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver truſt too much to any world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power, ſince Fortune or Fate (uſe the words as you pleaſe) did maintain an Empire ſo ſoveraign and arbitrary over the beſt laid Counſels, and moſt cautiouſly contrived deſignes; and ſince her inconſtancy is ſuch, that that man whom ſhe hath raiſed to ſuch a height this day that he ſeemeth her Darling, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſhe maketh him ſo miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that he may ſeem to be her ſport and ſcorn. It is ſhe who ſports her ſelf with our moſt ſage contrivances, and laughs in the face of the moſt ſerious-looking Councellor, and tells him his
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:50479:59"/>hopes are vain: It is ſhe who tells the Chymiſt after the labour of many years he ſhall never gain his Elixir, and breaketh his Crucible before his face, even in that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment when he thought her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Artillerie could not batter his deſignes: It ſhe who advanceth an <hi>Achitophel</hi> or <hi>Machiavel</hi> to honour, to affront Virtue. In fine, ſhe is an Ocean without limits, and will ſuffer none to be put to her but by Prudence, whoſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter take in the words of <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> the Pariſian, <hi>Toutesfois elle est de tel poids, &amp; neceſſité, qu'elle ſeule peut beaucoup: &amp; ſans elle tout le reste n'est rien; non ſeule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment les richeſſes, les moyens, la force. Vis conſilii expers mole ruit ſua. Mens una ſapiens plurium
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:50479:60"/>vicit manus. Et multa, quae natura impedita ſunt conſilio expediuntur, &amp;c.</hi> Charron en Liv. III. Dela ſageſſe.</p>
            <p>He took not his Religion from his Father, or Country, (as moſt do) nor ſucked it in with the milk of his Mother, but examined all Faiths throughly, and choſe that which he thought moſt conſonant to reaſon, and which gave the greateſt Honors to the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. He never ſordidly gave his aſſent to any Opinion out of fear, or for any other conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but Truth. He would not ſay a Piece was good becauſe it was <hi>Titian</hi>'s, or <hi>Tintarett</hi>'s, unleſs he found ſomething in it which convinced his judgment of its worth. In converſation he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes courteous and affable, not
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:50479:60"/>impoſing his opinion upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Magiſterially or Dogmatical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but if it admitted of any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute he calmly diſcourſed it, and was glad to be informed of truth from any mouth. When he ſaw any one not of equal experience with him he was pleaſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form him, and ſide with him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe rougher natures who would play upon him, and hope to raiſe the repute of their own parts upon his ſimplicity. He was far from the pedantry of thoſe who vaunt their knowledge and relate their Voyages in all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: He was not one who would make himſelf known at firſt, nor told them all he knew preſently. He was long in making a friendſhip, but when it was
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:50479:61"/>once ratified, no body was more true than he, and he would be alwayes ſure to make Virtue its Baſis. Nothing he deteſted more than their humour who boaſt of their Vices, who tell when they are drunk, or when at a Bawdy-houſe, and ſaid, ſince Nature com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thoſe offices to be done in the dark, it is impudence above compariſon to vaunt of them in publick. No one was juſter than he both to himſelf, and to his Neighbour. He ſaid, that the riſe of all juſtice is from the ſubduing of a man's appetite, and unleſs he had made his reaſon Plenipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiary over it to bring it to due o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, he could not without bluſhing rebuke any man for his crime.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:50479:61"/>
His conſtancy of Temper was great; he received all outward things with an even indifferency; his ſoul was never elevated by the careſſes of proſperity above its genuine temper, nor dejected by the frowns of adverſity below it. His valour (which is properly the ſtrength of the ſoul, as fortitude is of the body) gave him an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to meet all difficulties (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever great) with a generous and ſevere gallantry, and made him alwayes ready to atchieve thoſe things which others would have fled from. This Virtue is of proof againſt all accidents; it arms a man cap-a-pee againſt all, even the rougheſt aſſaults. <hi>Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum imbecilitatis humanae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expugnable: quod qui circumdedit
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:50479:62"/>ſibi, ſecurus in hac vitae obſidione perdurat.</hi> Senec. This Virtue (as ſome fancie) is not only confined to the Military Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for however that may be more pompous and gaudie, yet it is not ſo genuine and perfect. For I pray tell me, is not he of a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er courage who can with patience receive the ſharpeſt accoſts of a Chronical diſeaſe, who can open his breaſt, and uncover his head to the fierceſt darts of miſery without repining, only becauſe his inward light tells him he ought not to ſpurn againſt the will of Heaven; then he who is led into an Army perhaps by a deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, or of prey, and is forced to ſight, becauſe if he doth not, there are ſo many to witneſs his
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:50479:62"/>cowardiſe. This (if it be a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue) is common to all, to the King and Peaſant, nay even to beaſts too, and hath not the leaſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple or tincture of truly Moral Philoſophical valour. The other is not an inconſiderate raſhneſs, but before it enterpriſeth any thing, it conſidereth the reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs and juſtice of it; it run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not ſuddenly into danger, but only defends it ſelf, and when it doth aſſault, it is upon a good and juſt account; nor yet doth it deſpiſe any, even the ſmalleſt danger, but hindereth it, (if it can) from growing greater. It al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo holds it ſelf obliged to defend the injured and oppreſſed, and in their ſervice will ſacrifice it ſelf freely. He alwayes ſaid they
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:50479:63"/>much to blame, who gave way to the humor of an impudent vaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Thraſo,</hi> who by an inſolent deportment, and ſierce counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or high expreſſion think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to acquire the name of valiant and brave, and to be the Cock of all them with whom he converſes; for by yielding to him one giveth him to believe he really is that, which a brisk cariage would aſſure him he is not; for he reſembleth a fierce and ſwelled billow which cometh rowling down amain, as if it would overwhelm the rock which ſtands in its way, but by its firmneſs it is broken, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſively glideth away at its feet.</p>
            <p>As his Prudence, his Juſtice, his Valour were great; ſo alſo was his Temperance. He was afraid
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:50479:63"/>to drink too deep of pleaſure leſt he might ſurfeit and vitiate his Palate. He ſaid he was moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed when Heaven allayed his joyes with ſome ſorrows, and that it would be the greateſt affliction to have none. He knew thoſe who eat greedily might be ſatiate, but not ſatisfied, and knew it was the curbing of his appetite which kept it at once in obedience and in health. He alwayes avoided ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancie in apparel, and ſaid the man ſhould adorn that, not that him. He uſed ſeverely to declare againſt drinking, and ſaid that a Drunkard ſuffered many wayes; for beſides his laying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf open to the rogueries, and over-reachings of thoſe with whom he converſed, every man
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:50479:64"/>that he met might diſcover his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the face, as when one ſees a Buſh he knows wine is there; He could not be reconciled to thoſe who by wine thought to advance their natural fancies, and enrich their ſentiments: He ſaid in the heat of it a man might ſay extraordinary things, but yet he might have ſaid thoſe when he was ſober better if his modeſty would have given him leave, but in that condition one vents all, even the moſt extravagancies. It moſt certainly ruines all a man's parts as well as his body; for however he may have ſome fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies remain which may make him acceptable in ordinary converſe, yet the main is gone: as when Palace is burnt, there may here
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:50479:64"/>and there perhaps remain a piece of a guilded roof, or an embroidered Canopy, they may ſerve to ſhew what Glories have been there, but they will neither defend the unfortunate owner from Rain or Snow. He ſaid, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, when he was allured by any pleaſure, ought to conſider not how far he deſired to enjoy it, but how far he ought; and that he was ſure it was a greater and more tranſcendent pleaſure to ſubdue an inordinate affection then to gratifie it, that it took off the boylings of our fevouriſh blood, and rendered us more capable of more ſolid joyes in thoſe calm and temperate Regions of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal bliſs, when our ſouls are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted of their groſſer vehicles.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:50479:65"/>He was alwayes more ſolicitous for his Countries good than his own, and alwayes preferred that to his own advantage. He alwaies looked upon the King as his head; between which and the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers there ought to be a good cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence, becauſe one cannot ſubſiſt without the other. He was not of the mind of thoſe Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers who ſerve their Prince only for reward, but he thought it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward enough to ſerve him. His counſels were alwaies wholſom, and healing, and he alwaies was againſt invading any man's right: He adviſed that his Country might be alwaies prepared, and ready to take up arms; for he ſaid, that either hindred an Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or a Surpriſe; nay, he ſaid
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:50479:65"/>they ought to make peace with ſwords in their hands, for ſo they might command good terms. He not only by theſe wayes gained the affections of his King (but what is ſeldom ſeen) of the Court alſo. He never cenſured nor judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any man's actions unleſs upon very good grounds; for he knew he ought not to do it unleſs he was free from all thoſe vices he accuſed him of; and he was ſure that every one ſets himſelf to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the actions of ſuch a man, and makes every his leaſt fault of greater bulk than really it is; for if <hi>Iſhmael</hi>'s hand was up againſt every man, it was but juſt that every mans hand ſhould be up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. He was not of thoſe who extolled their own actions
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:50479:66"/>above juſtice, and think all fancie, ingenuity and judgment to be confined to them, or their relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for he knew they raiſed the expectations of all for greater things than they could performe; but he gave Virtue her due ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe where ever he found her, and was ſo far from traducing, or detracting from any man, that he ſought to hide his faults, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal his infirmities: He knew the world too well either to confide in it, or love it: if he had any thing that we call a bleſſing conferred upon him he took it <hi>en paſſant,</hi> and valued it but as a little conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience which might ſupport him in his way to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above. He never affected Honour or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerment, which he ſaid were
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:50479:66"/>Mounts which indeed yielded a fair proſpect, whilſt the raies of the Kings favour played about them; but if they did ſhine once another way, a man would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly break his neck down. He never did any thing for applauſe, which he ſaid no wiſe man would be delighted with, ſince it roſe from the people who are Judges of nothing that is generous, or brave. When he grew aged, he could do that which few or none of his time could; he could take a proſpect backward of his whole Life with a great deal of delight; he ſaw no vices in it which could render it hilly, or black, but all fair Lawns, ſpruce Meadows, and gentle Rivulets. It was his deſire to have no coſtly Marble over his
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:50479:67"/>body but only a plain Stone with this Inſcription.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theodatus</hi> from Earth to Heaven's remov'd.</l>
                  <l>Who lov'd fair Virtue, and of her was lov'd.</l>
               </q> He ſaid the greateſt Emperour ought to have no longer an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph, becauſe if his Virtue would not build him a Monument which might tranſmit his name to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, he ought to deſire to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. Thus then he ſurrendred his fair Soul when he was full of fame and years, after he had long been the Joy of the Virtuous, the Delight of the Court, and the Oracle of the State.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="novels">
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:50479:67"/>
            <head>Three Novels.</head>
            <p>THe laſt Summer three or four Gentlemen of good quality went ſome few daies jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney out of the populous City of <hi>London</hi> to recreate themſelves, and to breath the air of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and by the exerciſes of it, to diſpel thoſe groſs humours which had gathered in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ariſing from a full diet, and an unactive life: They paſſed a few dayes very pleaſantly in hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hawking, fiſhing; and becauſe the night ſhould have its plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure too, they reſolved that every one in order ſhould entertain the reſt with a Novel, and they agreed (as being the moſt equal way) that fortune ſhould point
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:50479:68"/>out him who ſhould begin the courſe: the Lot fell to <hi>Caſſander,</hi> and he, after he had with much modeſty excuſed himſelf, and told the Company that he was ſenſible how unfit he was to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter ſuch a Province, beſpake them thus.</p>
            <div n="1" type="novel">
               <head>The Land-Mariners.</head>
               <p>IT is not long ſince in a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable City of <hi>France</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants did celebrate a great Feſtival with much jubilee, and mirth; and that the approach of the night might not give an end to it, after the ſolemnities of the Bon-fires, and Fire-works, ſome of the Youth (Sons to the chief Burgeſſes) in order to the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of their deſign reſorted to
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:50479:68"/>a Tavern, and there that they might be farther from the ears of the people, they made choice of an higher room; here the Bowls were crowned with wine, their conceits with wit, and the night with all manner of jollity, but half of it was not ſpent when the brisker ſpirits of their wine began to mutiny in their heads, and to wage war againſt their reaſons, ſo that at laſt the floods of it which they had powred in made them fancy themſelves to be upon real ones at ſea, and their Chamber to be a Ship cruelly toſſed upon them, and their reel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and falling made them ſuppoſe themſelves in a great deal of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſo that they thought the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way to the Haven of ſecurity, was to disburthen their Veſſel of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:50479:69"/>all its Cargo, that it might with more agility play upon and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the billows before the Storm; they now begun to throw their Tables out of the Window, with their Stools and Doors, and all the Houſe-hold-ſtuff; with theſe they had almoſt brained ſome of thoſe who paſſed by; they immediately repair to the Magiſtrate, and acquaint him with the Riot, and deſire his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to ſuppreſs it; he gives his Warrant to his Serjeant to ſearch for, and apprehend them; he accompanied with other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers finds, and ſeizeth them: at his entrance ſome of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, (who had it is poſſible read the Poets when they were at School) with a great deal of joy imagine him (becauſe he carried
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:50479:69"/>a great ſtick) to be <hi>Neptune,</hi> and thoſe with him his <hi>Tritons</hi> come to their ſuccour; one of them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, who had all night had the head of the Table, and to whom the reſt of the Board ſeemed to pay ſome reverence, ſtood up with the help of his Chair, and with a great deal of ſubmiſſion addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf to him in theſe words: <hi>Great</hi> Neptune! at this the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant ſeemed much incenſed, (as being a man not much underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding humor) and grew very brief with him, &amp; would in that inſtant have carried him away, becauſe he called him out of his name; but one who it ſeems was a wittier brother than the reſt, deſired Mr. Serjeant to forbear a while, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he thought there might be ſomething of conceit in this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:50479:70"/>ſo that he gave him li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and he proceeded. <hi>Great Divinity of the Seas! thou art come most opportunely to the relief of the most miſerable and distreſſed of all thoſe whom the large Canopy of Heaven doth cover! for ever ſince we entered the Borders of thy Empire, we have been toſſed with croſs and impetuous Winds,</hi> (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Weights of the Town who played upon Cornets and Haut-bois) <hi>which have ſo enraged thy ſubjects the waves against us, that they have ſometimes mounted us above the greatest heights of</hi> Tenarif, <hi>and again have thrown us ſo low, that we might have plucked Coral, or have ſnatched thy</hi> Thetis <hi>from thy arms! In this condition we have been forced to cast over-board our richest Lading, and to ſend
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:50479:70"/>thoſe pearls into thoſe abyſſes again, from whence with ſo much hazard they have been taken; we have wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered through unknown and peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Regions without a Pilot or a Rudder</hi> (meaning the door which before they had plucked off the hinges) <hi>and without having touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon any Land but Shelves or Sand-beds, and without the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of that Cynoſure which ſhines out bright to the reſt of the happy Countries of thy Empire!</hi> (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Candle which before was extinguiſhed) <hi>This makes us im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore the mighty aid of thy arme and Trident,</hi>—and here he had almoſt ſaluted Mr. Serje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants feet, but by help being reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, he ſaith—<hi>and even now me-thinks the whole Ocean is but one great Whirlepool, and all the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:50479:71"/>Earth like our Veſſel in it</hi>— (with that one of the Company diſembogueth) <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Great King, the Terrors of thoſe Eddies!</hi> (with this another diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth) <hi>behold again thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued</hi> Alpes, <hi>and</hi> Appennines <hi>of waves!</hi> Then by chance looking out of the Window he eſpies the Multitude, (who alwayes upon ſuch an occaſion enter conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) gathered about the doors; then ſaith he—<hi>Behold with terror (Oh my Companions in miſerie) thoſe ſcaly Citizens attending the motions of their Great King ſtanding with open mouth to receive us!—all of them even from the Prince Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athan to the Peaſant Crab!</hi> at theſe words the Orator's tongue as well as feet failed him, and he lay pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and ſpeechleſs; another
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:50479:71"/>attempted to proceed, but he was found ſoon in the ſame predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo that now the Serjeant who in his nature was no great Judge or admirer of wit poſted them (becauſe it was too late to carry them before the chief Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer) to the Cage which uſually ſtands neer the Market-croſs: when they arrived there, they thanked the great Divinity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had heard their prayers, and brought them to a ſafe Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor. He left them there like <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi>'s Companions under the Charms of the Witch <hi>Circe,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging their ſtomachs as if they had been really ſea-ſick. You may imagine that in this condition, ſleep (without ſaying Prayers, or uſing any formal Ceremonies) ſoon crowned their Temples, and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:50479:72"/>bound them faſt till the Sun through the wide ſlits and crannies of their Chamber played upon their eye-lids, and moſt of the Infantery of the Town, at the Window of their Anti-chamber, adviſed them that it was time to wake. Some of them had not yet recovered their reaſon, and thoſe in whom it dawned by the illneſs of their lodging, and the over-charge of nature, were not able to hold up their aching heads. In a little time moſt of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, and gueſſed by the place where they were, (retaining ſome notion of it) at the nature of their offence; moſt of them were ſtruck with a deep remorſe for the crime, and all of them were deeply touched with the infamy of it; they therefore unanimouſly peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:50479:72"/>the Magiſtrate for enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and withall ſubmitted to what puniſhment he thought good to inflict upon them. Upon this they were releaſed, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried before him, where after he had given them a full account of their riot, with all the aggravating circumſtances he might, and told them the ill conſequences of this example, becauſe their qualities kept them from the uſual puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this vice, he thought good to command the laſt night's Oratour to give the others in a ſett Harangue the inconveniences of Drinking, which he did after ſome recollection, (as near as I can remember my Author's terms) in theſe words.</p>
               <p>When we cloud our Reaſon, and envelope it in miſts, what
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:50479:73"/>do we but turn our ſelves into thoſe brute animals from which (as Heaven's great Characteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick) it diſtinguiſheth us? Into what horrors of darkneſs do we throw our ſelves, when we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh that light which ſhould conduct us through the many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate Paſſages and Maeanders of this world! How unhappy are we ſince we make that which by a moderate uſe would give us a glad countenance, by an exceſs make us ſad! I ſuppoſe moſt of you before this time, Gentlemen, are ſenſible of the effects of our laſt night's voyage; and truly, whoever is a lover of this vice can be compared to nothing more fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than a ſea-faring man, who daily expoſeth himſelf and his fortunes to the rage of the bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:50479:73"/>and winds, whoſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is often ſo deſperate, that he deſpairs of a Port unleſs the hand of Providence ſteereth him to it: ſo he layeth his fortunes, his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets proſtrate at the feet of any Rogue, and putteth himſelf into his mercy; which dangers, if he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, it is by the care of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and the conduct of his kinder ſtarrs. If we gravely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon this action, how many things ſhall we find we have to bluſh for! and how many lives we have endangered beſides our own! How many dayes muſt we paſs in pennance for theſe few hours pleaſure! Think whatever extravagancies we have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted we muſt dearly anſwer them, a man cannot plead he was not himſelf, ſince he laboured under a
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:50479:74"/>voluntary madneſs. What ſad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances doth this Morning bring to us? and what would we not give to expiate our crime? <hi>Alexander</hi> that Great Conqueror being once overcome with theſe ſpirits, killed his deareſt friend <hi>Clytus,</hi> and when he underſtood it, would needs have ſacrificed himſelf to his <hi>Manes.</hi> This one vice opens to us a deluge of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; it prepares us to kill a King, or burn a City; to murther a Brother, or betray a Friend. But yet we ſee men contending with a ſtrict vigor and earneſtneſs, as if they were to gain an Olympick Prize, to conquer one another at this weapon, whilſt he who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the Palm is obliged to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with thoſe whom he hath transformed into Beaſts, and at
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:50479:74"/>laſt is forced to ſubmit himſelf to its powers. <hi>Seneca</hi> gives you the effects of Wine in the perſon of <hi>Mark Anthonie,</hi> of whom he ſpeaketh thus. M. Antonium, <hi>Magnum virum, &amp; ingeni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nobilis, quae alia res perdidit, &amp; in exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos mores, &amp; vitia non Romana rapuit quam Ebrietas, nec minor vino</hi> Cleopatrae <hi>amor? Haec illum res hostem Rei-publicae, haec hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſuis imparem reddidit, haec crudelem fecit, cum capita Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum civitatis coeanti referrentur, cum inter apparatiſſimas epulas lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> regales, ora ac manus proſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum recognoſceret, cum vino gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis ſitiret tamen ſanguinem, &amp;c.</hi> Ep. Lxxxiii. Add to this, that it infeebleth the nerves, looſeneth the limbs, infects the breath, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiateth the complexion, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:50479:75"/>the whole body, as well as mind, uſeleſs to ones Country, or Friend. I hope now your own experience, and my arguments (whatever they may be) have made you ſenſible enough of your crime, and will perſwade you to applaud the care of providence, which hath brought you to an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven where reaſon, or your <hi>Palinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> was drowned; and I hope you will never again attempt ſuch a voyage, though gales never ſo fair, or ſeas never ſo calm invite you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="novel">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:50479:75"/>
               <head>NOVEL II. <hi>Friendſhip ſublimed.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>By Lot</hi> Theogenes <hi>was to entertain them the ſecond night, who, after paying ſome civilities to</hi> Caſſander's <hi>Relation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan thus;</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF ſome of thoſe beauteous Towns which crown the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Banks of the <hi>Loire</hi> exceed <hi>Tours</hi> in elegancy of ſtructure, none of them come near it for commodiouſneſs, and pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſituation: (<hi>Tourin,</hi> the Country about it being called by way of excellence, <hi>Le Jardin die France</hi>) The ſweetneſs of the air, and the other conveniences of the place oft-times have brought peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:50479:76"/>thither to enjoy them; and amongſt many others a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of that Country, of a noble Family, and ample fortunes, was reſolved with his Wife and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily to reſide there for a Summer-ſeaſon. He had been bleſt with a fair and ingenious Offspring; but above the reſt his eldeſt Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who was named <hi>Charlotte,</hi> was fair and chaſt, and as well for the beauties of body, as mind, had ſcarce an equal, but no ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour over all <hi>France:</hi> She had not continued here long before her eyes produced their uſual ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and captivated all men in the place, and brought them to be either admirers, or lovers; and what is more, the women (who commonly like men of a Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, envy and decry one another)
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:50479:76"/>became Proſelytes to her Virtues, and owned, that not only them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but all whom they had ſeen were much inferiour to her; and if ſhe had not Adorers from all parts of the Nation, it was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe her Graces could not charm them, but becauſe her fame had not yet reached them.</p>
               <p>This new Flame which inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Town, ſpurred on the Youth to little Gallantries, and Gentileſſes more than before, and made them more earneſt in their Tiltings, and Juſts; and more ſplendid too, each ſtriving to go beyond the other, as well in his Horſes, his Habits, and Capari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as in the dextrous and grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful menage of his Weapon: and every man endeavoured the beſt he could to make himſelf (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:50479:77"/>to the then modiſh term) the leaſt unworthy of her; and whoever could but gain a ſmile, or a glance from her, wonne a Prize of greater value to him than the wealth of <hi>Peru,</hi> or <hi>Mexico.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of all thoſe who with ſo much earneſtneſs courted her favours, no one had it or deſerved it more than young <hi>Du Perrot,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from <hi>Paris</hi> thither ſome moneths before, for the ſake of the air: he was a man well-born, and of good fortunes, and one who it is poſſible would not have been diſcouraged by her Parents, if he had by them addreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to her. But though he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through the glaſs of modeſty could not ſee himſelf ſo well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded as he was, and wanted that aſſurance which he juſtly
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:50479:77"/>might have had; yet he did not fail to ſhew himſelf to her upon all occaſions, in the beſt equipage he could, either at the running at the Ring, and thoſe kind of ſports armed <hi>en Cavalier,</hi> or upon the Mall, or at the Balls, where he conſtantly had the honour to dance with her; which Exerciſes he performed with an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary mien; he embraced all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of diſcourſe with her, and, <hi>in fine,</hi> he uſed all means by which he might endear himſelf to her: ſo that at laſt, ſhe, though young, being not altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of love, and knowing that though ſhe was ſo univerſal a Conquerour, ſhe might, when cloſely beſieged, yield to a noble Aſſailant upon good tearms with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſhonour; began to cheriſh,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:50479:78"/>and foment, and indeed to be pleaſed with her growing flame; and now ſhe gave him liberty free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to entertain her publickly upon every occaſion, and had pretty well learnt the language of the eyes, (for in love they ſpeak much) ſo that now the fame of their affections was ſpread through the Town, which begot her Lover a great many Rivals: he notwithſtanding theſe publick favours, in private had hitherto kept his diſtance; (though the truth is, thoſe kindneſſes which he received from her, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the wants of that cunning, and counterfeit reſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of thoſe, who bred at Courts, would have made men of leſs prudence and caution, to have more haſtned their addreſs)
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:50479:78"/>but now he was no longer able to dally with thoſe flames which he ſo long had ſtood ſo near, and which now had ſcorched him ſo ſeverely: he therefore reſolves one day to go to her father's houſe, pretending a viſit to him, but with an intention to open himſelf to her; when he arrived there, he found according to his deſires, both him and her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from home, and being advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that ſhe was alone in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, he enters it, where after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received her pardon, which he ask'd for invading her privacy, and which ſhe eaſily granted, to one for whom ſhe had ſo great an eſteem, ſhe entertained him thus, perhaps to divert that diſcourſe which ſhe apprehended he would begin, Monſieur <hi>Du Perrot</hi> (ſaid
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:50479:79"/>ſhe) juſt as you appeared at the end of this Walk, I was putting away the hours with <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> and I was juſt in that part of it where <hi>Statira</hi> dealt ſo cruelly with the brave <hi>Oroondates</hi> when he firſt diſcovered his love to her, and I was accuſing her very much both of ingratitude, and incivility. Madam (replied he) this argues a great deal of compaſſion in your nature, to pitty the paſt afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe whom many Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of years have ſeen dead; and this may make him who hath the honour to wear your chains, hope a good return to his paſſion from ſo high ageneroſity of mind: Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly (continued ſhe) no body, without great injury to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, can with ſeverity repulſe a man, who, like <hi>Oroondates,</hi> comes
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:50479:79"/>encircled with all the advantages of Birth, of Fortunes, of Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whoſe head was crowned with all the honours, and wreaths of Peace, and whoſe Shield For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune had hung thick with all the favours of warr; It is ſure Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam (returned he) that ſhe was to blame, when ſhe exerciſed ſo great a ſeverity towards him; but yet it was not only upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his birth, and atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that he deſerved her love; for if thoſe muſt only weigh, no one but an <hi>Oroondates</hi> can ever pretend to a Miſtreſſes affection: but her fault lay in not receiving his ſo great paſſion, his ſo true affection with an equal one; nor by ſaying this, do I diſallow but <hi>Oroondates</hi> was as great an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of heroick gallantry, as the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:50479:80"/>world ever produced; but yet I muſt ſay, if other men are not ſo famed as he, it is not becauſe they want his parts or Courage, but becauſe thoſe opportunities which he had, are not offered them to exert them. There is no one who loves (anſwered ſhe) who can want a ſubject for his Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; for he will range the world for adventures, by which he may render himſelf acceptable to her whom he adores. * Madam, (preſſing her hand, and kiſſing it) if Love will require ſuch ſervices, no body ſhall go farther than <hi>Du Perrot</hi> to perform them, if his fair <hi>Charlotte</hi> command him; Sir (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted ſhe) pulling away her hand with much indignation, I never underſtood that love was an effect of friendſhip before; if
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:50479:80"/>I admitted you to ſome familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity upon the account of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I did not expect it could have produced the former; but ſince you ſo groſsly miſconſtrue my actions, know that <hi>Charlotte</hi> hath no thoughts which may not be arraigned before the ſtricteſt Tribunal of Virtue, and appear chaſt even though <hi>Lucretia</hi> her ſelf ſat Judge there. Having ſaid this, ſhe turned into another walk which led to a Grotta, where ſhe continued moſt part of the day, leaving him in the higheſt agonies which ſlighted love (the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of misfortunes) could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce. He ſtood long unmoved in very great diſorders, till at laſt recovering his reaſon a little, and, conſidering where he was, he found it unſafe for his affairs, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:50479:81"/>to purſue her, or to ſtay lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in that place, where he might ſoon be diſcovered by her Father or Mother, who uſed to paſs the Evening there. He therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired to his Lodging, where he ſpent the night in very great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietudes. In the Morning <hi>De La Hire</hi> (one for whom he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained a very great affection, and whoſe accompliſhments did indeed deſerve it) according to his cuſtome enters his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where he found him in an humour contrary to that he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; for whereas before un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asked he was wont to relate to him the adventures of the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding day, he could now ſcarce pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure one anſwer to a great many queſtions; he then began to accuſe him, and tell him, that by this
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:50479:81"/>reſervedneſs he would at once both loſe his friendſhip, and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: he told him on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that if he would be free, nothing ſhould be too hard for him to undertake to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date him; that his fortune and his blood ſhould weigh little with him, if at their expence he might procure his advantages: he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured him by all their ſacred oathes, their mutual vows and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, after he had long thus preſſed him, and found that the true ſource of his diſtemper was a Miſtreſs, he thought to have driven it away by raillerie, telling him, he imagined that he had known better things than to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be teather'd in one place of the Common, when he might have the liberty of the whole, that
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:50479:82"/>he would ſoon be weary of his one diſh, though a <hi>Biſque</hi> or an <hi>Oglio,</hi> if he fed of it every day. But he found theſe not at all ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifique, and that his pallat now ſo much out of temper diſguſted all things which it deſired before; he now perceived his Friend lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing, and pining, and to his great grief, almoſt grown out of his knowledge in 24 hours; ſo that he ſaw he was now to apply himſelf ſeriouſly to his affairs, and to labour his recovery by the beſt means he could; but before he undertook any thing, he conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Du Perrot,</hi> and deſired his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions how he might ſerve him; he found him loth to give <hi>Charlotte</hi> any farther trouble; but upon conſideration it was found, an application to her was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite.
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:50479:82"/>
                  <hi>De La Hire</hi> reſolves to wait upon her to know her reſolution. It was not difficult for him to find an opportunity, for that very Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon upon a viſit he made to her Father, with other Company, he took the occaſion to divert her, where after a little diſcourſe he told her, that that affection which his Friend had entertained for her he was ſure was as true as ever any was, and as pure as the flames which aſcend from Altars to thoſe Heavens which behold and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge all injuſtice, and will ſee that it ſhall have thoſe returns, and be crowned with that ſucceſs which it merits: did you but ſee in him, Madam (continued he) the effects of your own ſeverity, what a Skeleton he is as well in mind as body; how meagre and
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:50479:83"/>withered he is, who before was one of Natures choiceſt Pieces; and how dejected and mean that ſoul is now, which before breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing but generous and mighty things, you would (if any pitty inhabit your breaſt) weep, and weep ſo inceſſantly, that your tears ſhould never end till you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came like him: Ah Madam (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded he) if your love may not, let your generoſity at leaſt ſave a great Soul for whom all <hi>France</hi> will be beholden to you. Thus he laid open to her the height of his merit, omitting nothing that his friendſhip could dictate, or his own virtues could challenge. He found her words wary, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a whole reſignation of her ſelf to her Fathers will, which was only to lock or open her breaſt
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:50479:83"/>alone. Though theſe anſwers ſpoke indifferency, and ſeemed cold, yet any body might perceive a flame through them; and that by them ſhe only hinted to <hi>Du Perrot</hi> what way to proceed. <hi>De La Hire</hi> pretty well pleaſed with this, haſtens to his friends Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to unload himſelf, where he found him very diſconſolate, and wholly given up to thoughts: at his entrance he wore the moſt cheerful looks he could put on, which a little encouraged his Friend too; and then at once he ſatisfied his expectations and doubts, with the beſt conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that her words would bear, and gave him ſo much comfort, that in a little time he began to recover his former condition, and at laſt he grew very well by the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:50479:84"/>applications of his beſt Phyſician, Hope. In which ſtate we will leave him, and turn our Pen to another more comical, but no leſs adventrous Amour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="novel">
               <head>NOVEL III. <hi>The Friendly Rivals.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT this time a <hi>Germain</hi> and a <hi>Fleming</hi> were in the ſame Penſion in the Town, and had ſtruck a great Ligue of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; the victorious darts of the God of Love, pointed with rayes taken from <hi>Charlotte</hi>'s eyes, pierced at once the hearts of both of them (ſo united were their fates) even through thoſe mighty ramparts of Fat which did defend
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:50479:84"/>them. They now refined, by theſe new kindled flames altered their cuſtoms and dreſs; they greaſed not their Cloathes ſo much, and appeared oftner in clean Linnen: but though they became more gay, yet there was a kind of tawdrineſs in their Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, which diſtinguiſhed them from the reſt of Mankind; for they would wear their Laces with deeper, their Swords longer, their Poynts bigger than the Mode; they would daub their heads with a whole pot of Jaſmine at once, and then ſhew a pound of powder above it; and in fine, they would do every thing in exceſs, becauſe they loved ſo; a day did not paſs in which they walked not by her window three or four times, and when ſhe took the air, her ſhadow
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:50479:85"/>did not more ſurely attend her than they; they were ſure to gain an acquaintance with all thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Town, who kept the doors of the Ballets, and then would behold their Goddeſs from the foot of the room: this ſhe obſerved at laſt, and ſeeing them Fellows ſo deſpicable, ſhe thought without injury to her reputation, that ſhe might make her advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the humour, and improve it to very good ſport: In order to this, whereſoever ſhe met them, ſhe failed not to give ſome mark of her affection, either by unvail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or a nod, or ſmile, which they both received with mighty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies, and each took to himſelf; for the <hi>German</hi> was ſure ſhe could never affect ſo ugly a fellow as the <hi>Fleming,</hi> and he on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:50479:85"/>ſide thought that ſuch a rough-caſt piece of Nature as the <hi>German</hi> could never gain her; ſo that they, though Rivals, continued very good friends, and would never part, for they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried one another about for foyls. Thus they were both extreamly pleaſed, but grew now very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient to have ſome nearer proofs of that affection which they were both already aſſured of: they could not imagine how they ſhould introduce themſelves, for though their follies had made them known enough to the Daughter, they were altogether ſtrangers to the Father; (for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they were fellows ſo incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, that no body of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree took notice of them) yet one of them at laſt diſcovered
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:50479:86"/>that a Maid who ſerved in their Penſion, was acquainted with <hi>Cleorin, Charlotte</hi>'s Woman, one who had all the cunning and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleties of her ſex, and therefore the fitteſt in the world to cajole theſe fellows; and ſhe was the fitter too, becauſe ſhe had heard ſomething from her Miſtreſs of their humour: They wonne by ſome ſmall gift this Wench to their party, and ordered her to ſee if ſhe could perſwade her to meet two Gentlemen at a Tavern that afternoon, who though unknown to her, yet had ſomething to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver which might turn to her advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: You may think this had been an uncouth propoſition to her if the Meſſenger, who was privy to the whole deſign, had not diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to her; ſhe then gave her
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:50479:86"/>promiſe, being aſſured of booty, and at the hour of three ſhe failed not to meet at the place appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and there ſhe met the two Lovers who had expected her a while with ſome impatience. When they begun to open the affair to her, ſhe ſeemed to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with what confidence they could propoſe to her to betray her Lady, ſhe told them, offering to go away, that ſhe expected an entertainment anſwering their meſſage, ſomething which might have been her advantage; but now on the contrary, they offered that which would not only ruin her fortune, but her reputation, which ſhe valued much more: for all this, a little time being paſſed, and ſome few promiſes on their ſide made, ſhe ſeemed to incline
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:50479:87"/>to them, and at laſt was wholly wonne. They then proceeded to diſcover themſelves, but ſtill one obſtructed the other in his ſtory: ſhe demanded how it was poſſible ſhe could ſerve them both? for her Lady had but one heart, and ſince that could not be divided, it could belong but to one of them: they, both aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of ſucceſs, agreed of one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, aſſuring her, that whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Charlotte</hi> ſhould declare for one, the other in that moment would deſiſt. This ſeemed very ſatisfactory to all; they only now deſired to know the time and place, when and where they might attend <hi>Charlotte</hi>'s deciſive ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. She ſaid ſhe could not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to that, till ſhe knew her or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in it; ſhe therefore at preſent
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:50479:87"/>begged their pardon, and aſſured them, that before the night of the next day ſhe would ſend to their Conſident at their Lodging her Ladies reſolution. At her depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing each gave her five Piſtols; but the <hi>German</hi> ſlips out after her, (which the other ſaw, and was much pleaſed with it, thinking he might ſpare his pains ſince ſhe was ſurely his) and deſires her in particular to repreſent his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to her Lady, and to give her that Letter, and if ſhe could, to procure an anſwer to it; and withal he preſented her a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Ring, which ſhe willingly accepted, and promiſed her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours: The <hi>Fleming</hi> at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn ſeemed to chide him, and told him, he feared he had done him ill offices, and then running out,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:50479:88"/>gave her a Letter, and deſired the ſame, giving her five Piſtols more, and then gained the ſame promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. But now you muſt imagine them ſomething impatient till the arrival of the wiſh'd for hour; but though this time they could not ſee her, yet ſhe remained a conſtant object to their minds. they employ'd the reſt of the day, according to the cuſtom of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantick Heroes, of whom they had read in Poetry, and compoſed many Sonnets &amp; quaint Anagrams (as moſt agreeable to their capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities) which after the diſcovery of the Amour, made very good ſport about the Town: but I ſhall omit to ſet them down here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their numbers are ſo Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thick and Barbarous, that they were more fit to be ſung to a
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:50479:88"/>Trumpet than a Lute. But now the time and the Letter at once arrived, directed to both, which contained theſe words,</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>AS ſoon as the Moon appears come to the back door of the Garden, opening to the River, which ſhall be unlocked to receive you, and there when her affection will force her to declare her ſelf, you may behold the bluſhes of</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>CHARLOTTE.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>You need not doubt but they obſerved their time to a moment; for they had been walking by the river near the place an hour or two before, and juſt as their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Planet began to ſhine out, they made their entrance there with as much joy as if it had been
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:50479:89"/>Paradiſe, and expected as great felicities as it could afford. The <hi>German</hi> (though it was diſputed, becauſe they believed the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of their Miſtreſs) by the Priviledges of his Nation, as the Subject of an Emperour, took the door; but he had not walked many paces till he found himſelf in a pit above the middle, and a ring of iron cloſe claſped about him with a lock, which he could by no means open, and held him ſo faſt, that he could not move a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part downwards. He implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the aſſiſtance of his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, who refuſed it him, and ſaid he would not ſlight that oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity which his good Angel had preſented him to make him known without a Rival to his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and ſo left his poor friend
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:50479:89"/>in great diſtreſs. But he had not gone ſix paces forward before he retracted his former unkindneſs, and made it yield to generoſity, and reſolved to reſcue him; but in his return within two yards of the ſame place, to his great grief, he found himſelf in the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament. Then it was that they imployed the whole force of their eloquence in abuſing one-ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and becauſe they were not near enough to ſtrike, they bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered themſelves with the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons which the foil afforded, till they had ſpent all the gravel near them. Their rage now with their artillery ceaſed, and they thought it much better to unite their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt thoſe who had decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them, than to contend be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt themſelves. When they
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:50479:90"/>were in theſe thoughts, <hi>Charlotte</hi> and her Maid of a ſudden iſſued out of a neighbouring Grove, clad like good ſpirits (though they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not ſo to them) all in white, with white rods in their hands, going round them, and waving them above their heads, but ſeeming to take no notice of them, and ſung</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We muſt make theſe Walks and Groves</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Free from the dreggs of mortal Loves,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And clear them from th'un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean abodes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of croaking froggs, and creeping toads;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For</hi> Oberon <hi>the Fairie King</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fair</hi> Mab <hi>his Queen will hither bring,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="173" facs="tcp:50479:90"/>
                     <hi>And they muſt dance, and we must ſing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And they muſt, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then they stood ſtill and cried,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Come! O come without delay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ye Goat Prancers of the Groves,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Leave your Embraces, leave your Loves,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And cleanſe the mighty Monarchs way.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Then entred two Servants of the houſe dreſſed like Satyrs, with two great Buckets of water for a luſtration, and emptied upon each of their heads; with that they both cried and begged they would releaſe them, which <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotte</hi> and her Maid by laughing
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:50479:91"/>almoſt diſcover themſelves; with that the Satyrs ſeemed angry, and ſaid.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bold Mortals, how durſt you be here,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When</hi> Oberon <hi>was to appear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To prie into the unknown Rites</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of Fairie Ladies and their Knights,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſearch into the hidden ſport</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of the happy Fairy Court?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Stay till the King himſelf doth come.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>With this a company of Boyes dreſſed like Fairies come in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and caper round them ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:50479:91"/>and pinching them ſeverely; the <hi>Germain</hi> much ſurpriſed and affrighted, deſired to know which was the King, who when he was ſhewed to him, told him that he ſerved a mighty Emperour, and one who would revenge the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of his Subjects when they could not enjoy the Priviledges of the Law of Nations, which ſuffered all ſtrangers, guilty of no offence to come and go freely: To whom the King ſaid,</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thy Master, fool, doth but command,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Compar'd to mine, an inch of Land:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My ſpacious Empire is the Air,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And the lov'd Breaſt of</hi> Mab <hi>the fair.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:50479:92"/>
With that they contracted their Circle, and only run about him, and pinched, till he almoſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakned the houſe with his cries, which made them all run away, and leave the unfortunate Lovers as they found them, where they continued till the Sun bid the World Good-morrow, entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves with the ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Adventure, and the many circumſtances of their mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune. At this time the Gard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner enters the Garden, and ſeeing two men in this poſture, growing half out of the earth, ſtarted back; and it is poſſible if he had been read in the Poets, he might have thought that <hi>Cadmus</hi> had killed another Dragon, and had made choice of that place to ſow the teeth in: but he having no ſuch
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:50479:92"/>ſentiments, preſently runs in and gives the alarum to the houſe, ſo that it came to the Maſter's ears, who going to the place, would have apprehended them for Theeves, till his Daughter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him with the whole Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, which pleaſed them all as much as it diſpleaſed the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Lovers, who were ſo abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with it (for it was ſoon ſpread) that they were forced to remove to ſome more obſcure place of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next night after a little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capitulating, <hi>Theogenes</hi> proceeded thus. During the time of <hi>Du Perrots</hi> recovery, his friend did him all the beſt offices he could, and by his importunity he brought her to conſent to an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance of his viſit, which he
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:50479:93"/>payed with much joy, but alſo with much ſubmiſſion to her for that boldneſs which had wrought her diſpleaſure. She received him well, and excuſed her former ſeverity, which, ſhe ſaid, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from ſurpriſe, and aſſured him for the future of as much favour as might be conſiſtent with the duty ſhe was to pay her Father. He now renewed his diſcontinued viſits, and daily meetings, hoping by his aſſiduous ſervices to work a good end. In this ſtate their love was, when a thing which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the whole affair fell out. <hi>De La Hire,</hi> who had all this while laboured his friends quiet, was now unhappily concerned to do ſomewhat for his own; for by often treating to advance <hi>Du Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rots,</hi> loves, he found flames kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:50479:93"/>in his own breaſt by the ſame eyes: Nor was <hi>Charlotte,</hi> though ſhe carried it more ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, leſs charmed with his graces than he with hers. This accident wrought his great diſcontent, and had almoſt carried him to that diſtemper out of which he had brought his friend, who alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it with much grief, and ſtill ſollicited him, though with no ſucceſs, to know its cauſe. His thoughts were, ſhould I go to work mine own intereſt with her whom I adore, I ſhould at once prove falſe to her, and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to my friend; and ſhould I acquaint him, his generoſity per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps would give more than mine could receive; I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore repair to ſome ſolitary place, and there amongſt the Crags and
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:50479:94"/>and horrors of the thickeſt Groves will ſigh away my life, and prove my ſelf faithful to <hi>Charlotte,</hi> and true to <hi>Du Perrot.</hi> This ſaid, he makes out of the Town, and took the way which led to a neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Wood. His friend and Miſtreſs obſerving this from their window, reſolved to purſue him, and ſee if they could learn any thing. He had no ſooner entered the place at one ſide, but <hi>Du Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rot</hi> unſeen was got in at another, and <hi>Charlotte</hi> and her Maid (who was her Confident) at another; and ſeated themſelves under an hedge, by the advantage of which they could hear, and ſee him; and be undiſcovered. Aſſoon as he was ſat, he took up his lute, which his boy brought thither before, and ſtriking the ſtrings, ſung theſe
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:50479:94"/>words, which anſwered to the Notes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tell me! oh tell me all ye Groves</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Within whoſe ſacred breaſts do lie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The plaints and ſighs of faithfull Loves,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Was ever one more griev'd than I?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Love over me a Conqueſt makes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(Whoſe powers you know none can withſtand)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Friendſhip again thoſe Conqueſts ſhakes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ruines with a mightier hand.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Love doth make th' aſſault again,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So that of a cruel warre</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My breaſt muſt be th'unhappy Scene,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whilſt no ſide is a conquerour.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Therefore you powers who rule on high,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Direct me ſo that I may prove</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Happy once more, and fate defie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And true to friendſhip, and to love.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let not</hi> Charlotte's <hi>victorious eyes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>the juſt</hi> Du-Perrot's <hi>friendſhip wrong;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nor let his charms make me deſpiſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thoſe graces which from hers ariſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which Bards ſo oft in deathleſs notes have ſung.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <pb n="182" facs="tcp:50479:95"/>
At the end of this ſong his friends appear, which accident ſurpriſed him the more, becauſe he feared they had over-heard him. But <hi>Du-Perrot</hi> comes up to him with a clear and aſſured countenance, and ſaid, fear not my faithfulleſt friend, to make me miſerable, if you may at the ſame time render your ſelf happy; give <hi>Charlotte</hi> your love, ſo <hi>Du-Perrot</hi> may have your friendſhip. To you who have ſo long poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed the beſt part of me I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne the laſt, but the nobleſt, my ſoul, for by <hi>Charlotte</hi> I live. But yet think it not mean in me ſo eaſily to part with a life which with ſo much ſolicitude hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been preſerved, and in a time when I ſhould moſt of all deſire to prolong it, ſince <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotte</hi>
                  <pb n="183" facs="tcp:50479:95"/>is pleaſed to bleſs me with her affections: for it is but juſt that I ſhould ſacrifice my ſelf to my preſerver, and I am ſure Heaven thinks the virtues of <hi>De La Hire</hi> only fit to be joyned with thoſe of <hi>Charlotte.</hi> He here takes both their hands, and ſaid, go now happy Pair, go and enjoy the bleſſings of Cities, and of Courts! and leave here your at once un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy and unfortunate <hi>Du-Perrot</hi> to the quiet and ſolitude of theſe Woods, that here expiring he may pay his vows, and offer his prayers and ſacrifice for your eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happineſs! He here offered to joyn their hands, but they both went back, and <hi>De La Hire</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed himſelf thus; Wrong not your friend <hi>Du-Perrot</hi> in thinking he fears more than you
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:50479:96"/>to die; or that, whilſt he lives, you can over-come him in friendſhip or generoſity, though in all other things he yields to you. Aſſure your ſelf that you wrong her whom we both adore in believing ſhe would receive him who could ſo diſhonourably ſurvive his friend. I love a glorious fall as well as you! and what could render my Funerals more illuſtrious than that at my Grave <hi>Charlotte</hi> ſhould ſay here lyes the FAITHFULLEST OF LOVERS, and that <hi>Du-Perrot</hi> ſhould weep out, here lies the TRUEST OF FRIENDS. Goe, and be happy then together! and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy your many bleſſings in ſome happy place, to which your ſtars ſhall point you; and if ever you think or ſpeak of <hi>De La Hire,</hi> give him no other Character than that
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:50479:96"/>of a Faithful Lover, and a true Friend. Here was a profound ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence till the fair <hi>Charlotte</hi> broak it in theſe words; Much is due from me (generous friends) to both your loves, and from each of you to the other's friendſhip; but ſince it is not in my power to crown the ſame merits with the ſame rewards, I muſt deſire not to be preſſed to a declaration of my affections, but that both of you will accept my friendſhip, and give me yours, which will afford more ſolid and ſcraphique joyes than love, which grows leſs if it doth not determine with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment. To this, after ſome ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilities, they all conſented, and then begun a friendſhip which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but death could ever break.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="186" facs="tcp:50479:97"/>
And now perhaps ſome will ask to what end is all this from the beginning ſaid? to what doth it conduce? He who demands this, muſt know, that it was enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed to ſhew Virtue and Vice in their true colours. He muſt alſo know, that the Author did not undertake this in hopes to be crowned with the Crown of Fame, but rather with that that was given by the <hi>Romans</hi> to a good Citizen, who did then ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice his fortunes, and what he doth now, his reputation to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver his fellow-Citizens out of any imminent danger. But if any ſhould now ſeverely ſay, it is an impertinence, and ſhould blame the deſign for the error of its me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nager; he muſt know that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinences
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:50479:97"/>are to be driven out by impertinences, (as fire out of a burnt finger is by fire) that he who is guilty of them, ſeeing their inconveniences in another perſon, may in himſelf avoid them.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:50479:98"/>
            <head>Emendanda.</head>
            <p>PAge 20. l. 13. for <hi>feareth</hi> r. <hi>ſerveth.</hi> p. 21. l. 6 <hi>perpetually</hi> r. <hi>perpetual.</hi> p. 35. l. 15. for <hi>make that</hi> for <hi>two,</hi> r. <hi>make it two.</hi> p. 36. l. 2. r. <hi>is ſo bad.</hi> p. 37. l. 4. r. <hi>or</hi> 2, <hi>or</hi> 3. p. 52. l. 7. <hi>leave out now, and hath.</hi> p. 59. l. 4. after the word ſtrife a <hi>Parentheſis in.</hi> p. 60. and l. 13. is to come in which was miſplaced by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake of the Preſs. p. 61. l. 1. for <hi>his</hi> r. <hi>the.</hi> l. 2. for <hi>his</hi> r. <hi>their.</hi> p. 64. l. 10. for <hi>ſoul</hi> r. <hi>ſons.</hi> p. 73. l. 5. for <hi>redence</hi> r. <hi>reſidence</hi> p. 74. l. 7. for <hi>by</hi> r. <hi>to.</hi> p. 76. l. 2. leave out <hi>ſhould.</hi> p. 77. l. 10. r. <hi>of the winds.</hi> p. 82. l. 6. leave out <hi>if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 1. l. 3. for <hi>higher</hi> r. <hi>lighter.</hi> p. 93. l. 3. for <hi>quam</hi> r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. l. 15. leave out <hi>him.</hi> p. 115. l. 13. for <hi>ſevere</hi> r. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cure.</hi> p. 117. l. 21. inſert <hi>were.</hi> p. 142. l. 10. for <hi>where</hi> r. <hi>when.</hi> ead. l. leave out <hi>or.</hi> p. 148. l. 19. r. <hi>who are bred.</hi> p. 152. l. 13. inſert (<hi>ſaid he</hi>) p. 161. l. 11. leave out <hi>with.</hi> p. 173. r. <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot-prancers.</hi> ead. pag. l. penult. leave out <hi>which.</hi> p. 183. l. 12. r. <hi>fertunate,</hi> pro <hi>unfortunate.</hi> The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is deſired to excuſe the miſtake of the Printer, in putting the <hi>The Moral State, &amp;c.</hi> over the <hi>Life of Theodatus,</hi> and the <hi>Novels.</hi> He is alſo deſired to excuſe the falſe pointings, and ſome other litteral errors.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50479:98"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50479:99"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50479:99"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:50479:100"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:50479:100"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="168" facs="tcp:50479:101"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="169" facs="tcp:50479:101"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="170" facs="tcp:50479:102"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="171" facs="tcp:50479:102"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="172" facs="tcp:50479:103"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="173" facs="tcp:50479:103"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:50479:104"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="175" facs="tcp:50479:104"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="176" facs="tcp:50479:105"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="177" facs="tcp:50479:105"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="178" facs="tcp:50479:106"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="179" facs="tcp:50479:106"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="180" facs="tcp:50479:107"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="181" facs="tcp:50479:107"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="182" facs="tcp:50479:108"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="183" facs="tcp:50479:108"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="184" facs="tcp:50479:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="185" facs="tcp:50479:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="186" facs="tcp:50479:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="187" facs="tcp:50479:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:50479:111" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:50479:111"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
